<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The queen of Nauarres tales Containing, verie pleasant discourses of fortunate louers. Now newly translated out of French into English.</title>
            <title>Heptaméron. English</title>
            <author>Marguerite, Queen, consort of Henry II, King of Navarre, 1492-1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1597</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 200 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06891</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855936</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21446</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06891)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21446)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 556:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The queen of Nauarres tales Containing, verie pleasant discourses of fortunate louers. Now newly translated out of French into English.</title>
                  <title>Heptaméron. English</title>
                  <author>Marguerite, Queen, consort of Henry II, King of Navarre, 1492-1549.</author>
                  <author>A. B., fl. 1597.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by V. S[immes] for Iohn Oxenbridge, and are to be solde at his shop in Paules churchyard at the signe of the Parot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1597.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Marguerite d'Albret's: Histoires des amans fortunez, commonly known as L'Heptaméron.</note>
                  <note>Preface signed: A. B.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21446:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21446:1"/>
            <p> THE Queene of Nauarres Tales.</p>
            <p>Containing, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erie pleaſant Diſcourſes of fortunate Louers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now newly tranſlated out of French into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device (McKerrow 289): "Device of an ox on a bridge, with the letter N, and Labore et Constantia"</figDesc>
               <head>LABORE ET CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STANTIA</head>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by V. S. for Iohn Oxenbridge, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in Paules churchyard at the ſigne of the Parot 1597</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:21446:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:21446:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To his aſſured good friend <hi>I. O. Stationer.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ir, you hauing manie times beene in hand with me about a booke intituled, <hi>The Queene of Nauarres Tales;</hi> which (as you ſay) you haue cauſed to be tranſlated out of French, at your proper charges, on mind to Print it, and you haue ſeuerall times bin in hand with me to write you a Preface. You know I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer read the Booke, and therefore I am not able to ſay what argument it holdeth, nor otherwiſe what it concerns, which were behouefull to be knowne to him that ſhal write a Preface: but the Title is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to grace the Booke, bearing the name of <hi>the Queene of Nauarres Tales;</hi> whereby any man may coniecture that the contentes are ſome pithie Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, written for pleaſure and recreation: and ſo great a Princeſſe vouchſafing ſo to honour them with her owne name, who can thinke but that the pleaſure is contained within the limits both of wit &amp; modeſty? For the curious conceited fellows that liue now in the world, thogh not poſſeſt with any
<pb facs="tcp:21446:3"/> great ſtore of malice nor wit, but are yet of ſuch a fine ieſting humor, that they wil dry-bob any man that writes, of what ſubiect ſoeuer. In ſteade of a Preface I will preſent them with a peece of an olde tale, a fiction, and fained, I know not by whom; but if the Author wil not be found, let me father it my ſelfe, the fable is this.</p>
            <p>Nature hauing many yeares agoe ſo waſted her treaſures, in the perfiting of womans beauties, that by her former prodigalitie, her perfections are ſo conſumed and ſpent, that the women of this age are enforced to ſupply their defects by periwigs &amp; painting, by bombaſting, and bolſtering, and ſuch other artificiall helps; the poore Lady (finding her owne ſcarcitie, not able to performe that excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as before ſhe had done in the feminine ſex) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined yet to make proofe, and to trie her cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning what ſhe could do in the maſculine. Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking the taske, with this ſetled curioſitie, ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned a man of ſuch excellent perfection in all his limbs and lineaments, that Nature herſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to wonder at her owne worke: and as the curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Artificer, who thinkes his labor to be but loſt, that is ſtill concealed and neuer brought to ſight, ſo Nature bringing forth this ſuperexcellent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage to be viewed, appointed him in ſuch a place where the people of ſeueral Nations had their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall recourſe: the firſt that paſſed by was a Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, who taking a full ſuruey of this new formed man, croſsing himſelfe, both his forehead &amp; breaſt; then throwing vp his handes with admiration to the heauens, hee ſaide with a lowde voice; O moſt
<pb facs="tcp:21446:3"/> glorious &amp; excelent creature in countenance, more amiable and louely than our lady of <hi>Loretta,</hi> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage more comly than S. <hi>Iago</hi> of <hi>Compostella:</hi> but how ſhall I extoll thy prayſes? my compariſons are too weake; I will therefore leaue thee and bleſſe Nature, who hath bleſſed her ſelfe in featuring of thee. Nature that ſtoode faſt by, where ſhe might both heare and ſee, and yet vnſeene her ſelfe, was wel pleaſed with this firſt ſalutation, and the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard thus departed. The next that came by was an Italian, and he (as the Spaniard before, but with alitle more circumſpection) taking the view of this goodly creature, fell firſt into a fit of wondering; from that, into an extaſie of praiſing, then to prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, that for a thouſand duckats hee woulde not haue his wife to haue a ſight of this temtation: and now he fell to ſwearing, that to preuent all perills, he would keepe her ſtill lockt vp in a chamber; and thus he went his way. With this Nature ſmiled to ſee the paſsionate demeanor of the iealous headed Italian. And let it ſuffice that I deliuer (though not in this particular ſort) how the people of ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations as they paſſed by, what praiſes and commendations they would all of them attribute to this handiworke of Nature, imputing it to bee without fault, blemiſh, imperfection, or any maner of defect: till at the laſt there fortuned to come by an Engliſhman, I think ſome of the ſame trauelling fellows whereof there are ſome, that running tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the world to ſeeke new faſhions abroade, doe loſe al their wits that they carried with them from home; or perhaps it might be ſome worthy ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:4"/> that if he hath but diſcharged a caſe of pifle-pots out of a Gentlemans chamber, ſeene an Enſigne three times ſpread in the field, puts himſelfe by and by into the arming doublet, the poyntes with the great ſiluer tagges, tied in the pitch of the ſhoulder: then at euery word he muſt be caled Mas Captain: then if hee haue but learned thus much of the new Diſcipline, as to ſay, Double your Rankes on the right hand, now againe as you were, double your Files on the left hand, cloſe your Ranks, open your Files: why ſo, this is enough to make him able to cooſin an hundred and fiftie ſouldiers of their pay. Now for table-talke you ſhal heare nothing out of their mouths, but of the ſcaling of forts, the aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of breaches, the taking of citidales, &amp; by theyr words they will ſeeme to vndertake the winning of a greater towne than <hi>Lysbourne,</hi> but with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charging two or three volies of oths. To conclude, when they are angrie, there is nothing in their mouthes but the ſtab; and when they are pleaſed, their greateſt friendſhip is not woorth an ordinary of eighteene pence. I ſpeake not to preiudice anie gentleman that hath trauelled for his owne experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whereof there bee many worthy of commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, nor to diſgrace any ſouldier that is of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, whereof there are none but are worthy of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: but I ſpeake of thoſe counterfeit Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that vnder theſe titles and pretenſes do coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce themſelues, taking authoritie to ſlander, ieſt, ſcoffe, and find fault at any thing. One of theſe priuiledged people now paſsing along the ſtreete, his geſture ſo gouerned as if he caried a whole com
<pb facs="tcp:21446:4"/> mon wealth in his head, his eyes ſo fixed as if hee were in the meditation of his miſtreſſe, his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſo graced, as a man might ſee a dicker of fools in his face, his ſalutation to ſuch as paſſed by was a nod with his head, and his hand clapt ouer his lips, which they do call the <hi>Baſsiles manus,</hi> his ſpeeches compendious and ſhorte, nothing but ſentences: this finicall fellow being now come to the place where Nature was yet abiding, reioycing to heare herſelfe ſo glorified for this excelencie of her work, he began as the reſt had done, to ſuruey euery part, euery proportion and lineament, from the top to the toe, he went about him, and round about him, behinde, and before, prying, and beholding wyth more curioſity than any of the reſt had done before him, and when he had lookt til he was wearie, ſaid neuer a word, but ſhaking a little his head was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, till nature ſeeing this ſtrange demeanor called him backe, and in curteous ſort demaunded of him how he liked of the obiect, that hee had ſo aduiſedly peruſed: to the which he anſwered; In faith it is not to be miſliked, it is a very goodly pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence, hanſome, comely, God had done his part, and he ſaw nothing but the man was well inough. But I pray ſaide Nature againe, what is it that you miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like? I perceiue by your ſpeeches there is ſomthing amiſſe, and therefore tell me what it is that you do thinke might be amended. Gentlewoman (ſaide he) ſeeing you preſſe me ſo farre, I wil deale plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with you; the fault that I finde is this, It is pitty that he is not an Engliſh man borne, but if hee had beene an Engliſh man borne, I coulde then haue
<pb facs="tcp:21446:5"/> commended theſe perfections, which I will nowe forbeare. And it is pitie (ſaid Nature) that thou art an Engliſhman borne; for if thou wert not an En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhman borne, I woulde ſo diſplay thy imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, which in regard of that renowmed Nation now I wil omit. This poore pedant meeting with ſuch a counter-buffe, thought it not good to fall a ſcolding with a Gentlewoman, but caling her curſt queane, went his way ſcratching of his head. And here an end of an olde tale.</p>
            <p>Now M. <hi>Oxenbridge</hi> I wil direct my text again to your priuate ſelfe, how ſhal you and I eſcape the gentle frump from theſe ſame perillous conceited fellowes, that will not omit to finde a fault at anie thing, nor wil not forbeare to breake a ieſt vppon any man? mary Ile tell you how weele ſtop their mouthes if we can, wee wil giue them the foole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand: I do not meane to any friendly Reader, that will ſooner winke at a fault, than finde a fault, but to theſe mungrell curres, that although they cannot bite, will yet ſtand aloofe and barke. And this <hi>Miſacmos</hi> in his Apologie of Aiax ſaith is a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, and he calles it <hi>Prolepſis</hi> or Preuention. Now if we by giuing the foole aforehand, could preuent them that they ſhould not ſnarle at vs, twere a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tricke. And why not? For now I remember me, I knew the practiſe of it long before I knewe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacmos,</hi> and learned it of a Gentlewoman that had borne a baſtard before ſhee was married, who for preuention ſake would cal whoore firſt, &amp; would raiſe ſlaunderous reportes of euery other woman, how honeſt ſoeuer, becauſe ſhe would brand them
<pb facs="tcp:21446:5"/> all with her owne marke. Call you this a Figure? No ſir, it was wit, and I warrant you it proceeded from a very quicke conceit: as how? Mary ſhee would not venture vpon a husband, til ſhe had made triall how ſhe was able to endure the bearing of a child: for <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia probata</hi> wittrieth all things. Sir, I do commend her for her wit; but by your leaue, if my wife were but halfe ſo wiſe, I would thinke that a Carte were fitter for her than a Coach.</p>
            <p>Well, I thanke you <hi>Miſacmos,</hi> we haue made a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle bold with your Figure, and I hope without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; and I ſee preuention is very good, but I like not of his preuention, that being a knowne cuckold himſelfe, and to preuent ill language, woulde hang hornes in the night at his neighbours doore: Like to a cunning fellowe that I know, I will not ſay a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie-catcher, but a ſcaulled ſquire named <hi>Will Cogge,</hi> a trencher ſcraping cullion but this other day, who in leſſe then a yeares cogging (being skilfull in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie) hath got more, then nowe by his trade heele get theſe ſeuen yeeres. This Canniball (I ſay) in the night would hang vp horns at his neighbors doors, that they might ſeeme as ſhamefull to the worlde, as hee ſhameleſſe: and nowe aſſociating himſelfe with one, a iolly fellowe, who though hee ſeeme to the view of the world (by the cariage of his body) a well accompliſht K: at armes, yet otherwayes, but a paul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſhifting wenching companion, when a man hath made the beſt of him; who becauſe hee might not haue the maidenhead of his neighbors wiſe the firſt night, but Iacke Drummers entertainment, after hee had ſhamefully demaunded it, runnes vp and downe
<pb facs="tcp:21446:6"/> 
               <hi>(threatning highly) in his hoſe and dublet like a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterleſſe man, with his collar turned downe round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his necke, making way for the halter, as one that were going to be hangd, to mince them as ſmall as fleſh to the pot. Well, birdes of a feather wil hang together; theſe two, knaues I found them, &amp; knaues I leaue them, and that is all the reckoning I make of them. Well, let them winch that are rubbed on the gall, but if they kicke, I will ſtand aloofe and crie, guppe olde Iade are you coltiſh? And when I haue a little laughed, I will leane my ſelfe to this olde axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome, Qui moccat moccabitur; the which in our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue may thus be interpreted, ſhee is a ſorie Lady that hath neuer a Ioynter. Thus M. <hi>Oxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> if you ſhall accept of theſe lines thus haſtily hatched, I hope the curteous Reader will not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and for the malitious I care not. Thus with my commendations to your ſelfe I ende.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your aſſured friend, A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21446:6"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>The Queene of Nauarres Tales.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="novel">
               <head>The firſt Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ Of a woman of Alancon that had two friends, one for pleaſure, the other for profite, which cauſed one of them to be killed that firſt perceiued her deceit, for the which ſhee obtained a pardon both for her ſelfe and her husband that was fled, who after that to ſaue a peece of money wherein hee was condemned, ſought counſell of a Coniurer; but his enterprice being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, they were both puniſhed.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Towne of <hi>Alancon,</hi> in the time of Duke <hi>Charles</hi> that laſt deceaſed, there dwelt an Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney that had married a gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of that countrey, more faire than honeſt; who by reaſon of her beauty, together with her light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, was greatly ſought vnto by a religious man, whoſe name I will conceale, for the reuerence of their ſtate, who to attaine to his deſire, entertained her huſband ſo wel, and vſed him ſo friendly, that being blinded with ſimplicitie, could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the lewdnes of his wife: but which is more, cauſed him to forget the affection that hee alwayes had to the ſeruice of his maſter and miſtris, in ſuch ſort, that of a faithful ſeruant, he became ſo contrary, that in fine he ſought by Coniurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to bring the Dutcheſſe to her end. This prieſt liued long time, in that maner with this wicked woman, which obeyed
<pb facs="tcp:21446:7"/> him more for deſire of money than for loue, as alſo that her huſband ceaſed not to incite her thereunto. But there was a yong man in the ſaid towne of <hi>Alancon,</hi> ſonne to the lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant generall, whom ſhe loued with ſo great affection, that for his loue ſhe was in a maner halfe beſide her wits. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ofttimes ſhe holp herſelfe by the prieſts means, by ſending her huſband foorth, whereby hee beeing buſied, ſhee might with better leiſure viſit the lieutenants ſonne. This manner of behauiour continued ſo long time, that for her profit ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the prieſt, and for her pleaſure receiued the other, vnto whom ſhe ſware that al the entertainement ſhe gaue vnto the prieſt was only by that means freely to vſe his companie, and that whatſoeuer paſſed betweene them yet ſhe ſaide the prieſt had obtained naught of her but wordes, and that he might be wel aſſured, that neuer any man but himſelfe ſhould reape o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſure at her hands. Vpon a day as her huſband went to ſee the prieſt, ſhe aſked him leaue to goe into the countrey, ſaying that the aire of the citie was ſomewhat contagious for her: and being at her country houſe, ſhe wrote vnto the lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants ſonne that he ſhoulde not faile about ten of the clocke at night to come vnto her, which he failed not to doe: but at the doore he found the maid that vſed to let him in, who ſpake vnto him and ſaid; Friend, you muſt now go walke ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, for your place is taken vp. Hee thinking her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had bin come, aſked her the cauſe: wherewith the poore maide pittying his eſtate, and perceiuing him to be ſo fayre, and honeſt a yong man, and one that loued ſo wel, and ſo litle beloued againe, opened her miſtris folie vnto him, thinking that when he vnderſtoode thereof, hee woulde blame himſelfe for louing ſo conſtantly. She told him that the prieſt was but newly come thither, and gone to bed to her miſtris, whom at that time ſhe looked not for, in that ſhe had not appointed him to come before the next day; but he hauing buſied her huſband about his affaires, was ſecretly come that night to viſite her. If any man euer diſpaired, aſſure your ſelues it was the lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants ſonne, who for that time would ſcant beleeue it, But
<pb facs="tcp:21446:7"/> to trie the trueth, he ſtayed at a houſe hard by till he ſawe the prieſt come foorth, not ſo wel diſguiſed but that he knew him better than he would. In which diſpayre hee went to <hi>Alan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> whicher, not long time after, his counterfet friend retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who thinking to abuſe him, as ſhe had often done, went to ſpeake with him: but hee ſaide ſhee was too holy (hauing touched conſecrated things) to ſpeake with him being ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable a ſinner as he was, whoſe repentaunce was ſo great that he hoped it could ſoone be pardoned. When ſhe perceiued her wanton life diſcouered, and that neither excuſe, oathe, nor promiſe neuer to do it againe would aught preuaile, ſhe made complaint vnto the Prieſt. And hauing conſulted with him, went and told her huſband, that ſhee coulde no longer ſtay in <hi>Alanſon,</hi> becauſe the lieutenants ſonne whome ſhee accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for her friend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſought continually to diſhonour her; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſhe deſired him to giue her leaue to ſtay at <hi>Argenton,</hi> thereby to ceaſe ſuſpition: her huſband that ſuffered himſelfe to be ruled by her, yeelded to her requeſt. They were not long at <hi>Argenton,</hi> but this wicked woman ſent worde vnto the lieutenants ſonne, that ſhee thought him the wickedeſt man at that time liuing on earth, and that ſhee had heard that hee ceaſed not openly to ſpeake euil of hir and of the prieſt, for the which ſhe ſwore ſhe would be reuenged. The yong man that neuer had ſpoken thereof but to her ſelfe, and that feared the prieſts diſpleaſure, with two of his ſeruants went ſtrait vnto <hi>Argenton,</hi> and found the woman in the Iacobins Church at euening prayer, where hee went and kneeled downe hard by her, and ſaid vnto her: Gentlewoman, I am come hither to proteſt vnto you by the liuing God, that I neuer ſpake to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of you to your diſhonor, but only to your ſelfe, and yet you haue committed ſo heynous an offence in my behalfe, as I haue not vſed halfe ſo many iniurious ſpeeches in your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe as you deſerue, for if either man or woman wil affirme that euer they heard it from my mouth, I am come hither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore your face to prooue them liers. Shee perceiuing many people to be in the church, and that he was accompanied with
<pb facs="tcp:21446:8"/> two luſty ſeruingmen, ſpake as ſoftly as ſhe could ſaying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, ſhe doubted not but he ſaid the truth, &amp; that ſhe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him too honeſt to ſpeake euil of any woman in the world, ſpecially of her, being one that loued him wel, but ſhee ſaide her huſband had ſome inkling thereof, wherefore ſhe deſired him that he would cleare himſelfe before him, whereby hee might be thorowly perſwaded of her honeſtie, which hee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vnto; and thinking to bring her home, tooke her by the arme: but ſhe tolde him it was not good for him to goe with her, for if he ſhould, her huſband would conceiue that ſhee had cauſed him to come. And therewith taking one of his men by the cloke, ſhe ſaid vnto him, let your man goe with mee, and when time ſerueth, I wil ſend him to fetch you, meane time goe you vnto your lodging: hee not fearing her conſpiracie, went thither, and ſhe being at home made his man that went with her to ſtay to ſupper, who demanded of her oftentimes when hee ſhould fetch his maiſter: ſhe anſwered hee woulde come time enough. When midnight came, ſhe ſent one of her ſeruants ſecretly to fetch him, who nothing doubting her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended miſchiefe, went boldly to ſaint <hi>Aignans</hi> houſe, where the gentlewoman ſtayed his ſeruant, whereby he had but one with him. And when he was at the dore, her ſeruant told him, that his miſtris would faine ſpeake with him before her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and that ſhe ſtayed for him in a chamber, only with his owne ſeruant, ſaying he ſhould do wel to ſend his other home, which he preſently did: and going vp a paire of darke-ſtaires, the Attourney that had ſet men to watch in a chamber hard by, hearing the noyſe of his feete, aſked who went there? and it was told him it was a man that woulde ſecretely come into his houſe. With that one <hi>Thomas Guerin</hi> a common mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, and by the Atturney hyred for the purpoſe, ſtrooke ſo many blowes with his ſword at the poore young man, that what defence ſoeuer he made, hee could not ſaue his life, but was preſently ſlaine. His man that in the meane time was talking with the Gentlewoman, ſaide vnto her, I thinke I heard my maiſter on the ſtaires, I will go ſee. But ſhe made
<pb facs="tcp:21446:8"/> him ſtay and ſaid; take you no care he wil come ſoone enough. But not long after hearing his maſter ſay, alas, I am dead, Lord receiue my ſoule, he ſaid he would go help him: yet ſhee ſtil held him ſaying, doubt not, it is nothing but that my huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band hath taught him how to leaue his youthful tricks: let vs go ſee; and looking downe from the ſtaires head, aſked her huſband what the matter was, ſaying, what haue you done? who replied, come downe and ſee. Nowe haue I reuenged you of him that lought you ſo much ſhame, &amp; ſaying ſo, with a poinyard that he had, thruſt ten or twelue blowes into his belly being dead, that liuing hee durſt not aſſaiſe. After the murther done, and that the dead Gentlemans ſeruants were both fled, to certifie his father: the ſaide <hi>Aignan</hi> knowing it could not be concealed, and that the Gentlemans ſeruauntes could not be allowed as witneſſes in lawe, and that not: anie man in the houſe had ſeene it done, but only the murtherers, an old maid, and a yong wench of fifteene yeres old, thought ſecretly to take the old maid, but ſhe found meanes to eſcape away, and fled into the Iacobins church, being the ſureſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to prooue the murther. The wench for a time ſtayed within the houſe; but he found ſuch meanes, that one of the murtherers inticed her, and he falling in loue with her led her to Paris, and there kept her in the common ſtewes, by the which meanes ſhe was not a lawful witneſſe. And the better to hide the murther, he cauſed the dead body to be burnt, and the bones that were not conſumed, to bee putte into a morter and ſtamped to pouder: ſending in al haſte vnto the Court, to aſke a pardon, giuing it to vnderſtand, that he had oftentimes forbidden his houſe to a certaine yong man, whom he ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his wifes behalfe, who notwithſtanding was come thither by night, ſecretly to ſpeake with her, and finding him at her chamber doore, more filled with rage than reaſon, had ſlaine him. But hee coulde not ſo ſoone diſpatch his letter to the chancellor, but the Duke and the Ducheſſe by the father of the dead man were certified therof, who to ſtay his pardon, wrote letters to the contrary. Whereuppon the vnhappy
<pb facs="tcp:21446:9"/> wretch perceiuing he could by no means obtaine it, fled with his wife, and diuers of his kinred into England: but before his departure he ſaid vnto the murtherer, (who at his requeſt had done the deede) that he had receiued expreſſe letters from the King to take him, and cauſe him to be hanged: but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the ſeruice he had done, hee ſaide hee was content to ſaue his life, and therewith gaue him tenne crownes to flie out of the realme. Which he preſently did, and neuer was ſeene againe. But the murther was ſo well prooued and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, not onely by the ſeruants of the dead man, but by the maide that ſaues her ſelfe in the Iacobins church, as alſo by the bones found within the morter, that in the abſence of the ſaid <hi>S. Aignan</hi> and his wife, the proces was made and ſued againſt them, whereby they were both condemned by default, and iudged to be hanged, their goods confiſeate to the prince, and 1500. crownes giuen to the father of the dead man, for the charge of the ſute. Meane time the ſaid <hi>S. Aignan</hi> being in England, and ſeeing that by courſe of law he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in France, did ſo much by his ſeruice vnto diuers Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, as alſo by the meanes of his wiues kinſmen, that the King of England wrote vnto the king to grant him pardon, and to reſtore him to his goodes and credite againe. But the king hauing vnderſtoode the heinouſneſſe of the fact, ſent the copie of the proces vnto the king of England, deſiring him to looke into it, and to conſider whether ſuch a fact deſerued par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; certifying him likewiſe, that the duke of <hi>Alancon</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had that priuiledge within his realme, to grant pardons for al faults committed within his Duchie. Al theſe excuſes not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, the king of England did not content himſelfe, but wrote ſo earneſtly therein, that in fine at his requeſt, the Attourney obtained his pardon, and thereby returned into Fraunce. But being at home, the better to accompliſh his iniquities, hee acquainted himſelfe with a certaine coniurer named <hi>Gallery,</hi> hoping by his meanes and diuelliſh art, to be exempted from paying the ſaid fifteene hundred crownes to the dead mans father. Which to effect, hee and his wife
<pb facs="tcp:21446:9"/> went diſguiſed vnto Paris, where his wife perceiuing her huſband with the ſaid <hi>Gallery</hi> to be ſo long time ſhut vp into a chamber, and made not her acquainted with the cauſe, one morning ſhe watched them, and ſawe. <hi>Gallery</hi> ſhew her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band fiue Images of wood, whereof three had their handes hanging downe, and two held vp their hands, and ſpeaking vnto him ſaid, we muſt make the like Images in waxe, and they that haue their armes hanging downe, ſhal be the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of ſuch perſons as we meane to conſume to death, but thoſe that hold them vp, ſhall be for thoſe of whom we meane to win the fauour. Then the Attourney ſaid, this ſhal be for the king, of whome I will be loued, and this for <hi>Monſieur Brinon</hi> Chancellor of <hi>Alancon. Gallery</hi> ſaid, you muſt ſet the Images vnder the alter where maſſe is vſually ſaid, with certaine wordes, which as then (ſaid he) I wil cauſe you to pronounce: and ſpeaking of the images that held their armes downe, the Attourney ſaide, that one of them was for Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Giles de Meſuil</hi> the dead mans father, as knowing wel, that as long as he liued, he would neuer leaue the ſute, &amp; one of the images, made for women that had the armes hanging downe ſhall be (ſaid he) for my Lady the Dutches of <hi>Alan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> the kings ſiſter, becauſe ſhe loued her olde ſeruaunt <hi>Don Meſuil</hi> ſo wel, and to the contrary, knew ſo much of the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneys villany, that if ſhe died not he could not liue: and the ſecond image of a woman hauing the armes downeward, hee ſaid was for his wife, as being cauſe of all his miſchiefe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well aſſured, ſhe neuer would amend her life. When his wife that ſaw all this through the key hole of the doore, and vnderſtood he placed her among the dead, thought it better to ſend him thither firſt: ſo that making as though ſhee went to borrow money of her vncle, being maiſter of Requeſts vnto the duke, ſhewed him what ſhe had heard and ſeene her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band do. Her vncle like a truſty old ſeruitor to the duke went vnto the Chancellor of <hi>Alancon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> aduertiſing him therof: and becauſe the Duke and the Dutcheſſe of <hi>Alancon</hi> were not on that day at the Court, the Chancellor went and tolde it to
<pb facs="tcp:21446:10"/> the lady Regent the queene mother, and likewiſe to the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe, who preſently ſent for the prouoſt of <hi>Paris</hi> called <hi>La-Barre,</hi> who made ſuch haſte, that he tooke the attourney and <hi>Gallery</hi> his Coniurer, who without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or anie con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>raine confeſſed their fault. Whereupon their proces being made, was carried to the King, to whome (ſome of the Court deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſaue their liues) ſaid in their behalfe, that by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts, they ſought but only to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his fauor, and not to deſtroy him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the king hauing his ſiſters life as deere as his owne; commanded that iudgement ſhould bee giuen in as ſtrict a maner as if they had practiſed his own death. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe the Ducheſſe of <hi>Alanſon</hi> his ſiſter, beſought him to ſaue the Attunies life, and to change his death into ſome hard and grieuous corporall paine; which was graunted her, ſo that he and <hi>Gallery</hi> were ſent to Marſeills, there to rowe in the galli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Saint <hi>Blanquart,</hi> where in they ended their dayes in great captiuitie; and thereby had meanes to confeſſe and acknowledge the greatneſſe of then ſinnes: and the wicked woman in the abſence of her huſband continued in her wickedne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more than euer ſhe did before, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſerably<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="novel">
               <head>The ſecond Nouel.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The pitiful and chaſte death of the wife of one of the Multiers of the Queene or Nauarre.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here dwelt in the towne of <hi>Ambois</hi> a multier that ſerued the Queene of <hi>Nauarre<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> ſiſter to <hi>Frauncis</hi> the French king, whoſe wife lay in childbed of a ſonne within the Cittie of <hi>Blois;</hi> whither the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> multier <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> receiue his quarters wages, leauing his wife at <hi>Ambois,</hi> lodging be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bridges: now he had a ſeruant that of long time had ſo deſperately loued his wife, that vppon a certaine day hee could not chooſe but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vnto her: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhe b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt woman, tooke it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reprooued
<pb facs="tcp:21446:10"/> him, but threatned to cauſe her huſband to beat him, whereby hemener after durſt venture to ſpeake vnto her, or once ſhew any countenaunce thereof, keeping it ſecret in his heart vntill ſuch time his maſter was gone abroad, and his miſtris in S. Florontines (a church belonging to the caſtle, and ſtanding farre from thence) at euening prayer. And he being at home without company, it came in his minde to ſeeke that by force and violence, which by prayer and ſeruice he could neuer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and to that end brake a planke out of the wall, between the chamber of his miſtris, and that where he lay, which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſide of the hed, as wel of his maiſter and miſtris, as of the ſeruauntes on the other ſide ſtoode cloſe vnto the wall, could not be perceiued, whereby his wicked pretence coulde neuer be eſpied, till vpon a time, ſhe being in bed with a yong wench of eleuen or twelue yeares old, and in her firſt ſleepe, this villaine in his ſhirt entred through the ſaide hole into the chamber with his naked ſword in his hand: but as ſoone as ſhe felt him by her, ſhe quickly ſprang out of the bed, diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him by all meanes and exhortations, that poſſibly an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt woman could deuiſe; but he that had naught but heaſtly loue, and better vnderſtood in the Mules language, than her honeſt reaſons, ſhewed himſelfe beaſtilier than thoſe beaſts with whome he had long continued: for perceiuing that ſhee ranne ſo faſt about a table that he could not haue his will, as alſo that ſhe was ſo ſtrong, that ſhe had twice looſed her ſelfe out of his hands, being in diſpaire neuer to haue his pleaſure while ſhe liued, gaue her a great blowe vpon the reines, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that if neither feare nor force could make her yeelde, yet paine would doe it: but he found the contrary, for that euen as a good ſouldier, perceiuing his blood, is therby more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to reuenge himſelfe, and winne his honour, ſo her chaſte heart inforced her much more to runne and flie out of the vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines hands, alwaies giuing him the faireſt words ſhe could, thinking by ſuch meanes to make him knowe his fault: but to the contrary he was ſo furious, that by no means he wold be ruled by her good counſel, giuing her diuers other blows,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:11"/> which to auoyd, ſhe neuer ceaſed to runne, as long as her legs would hold. But in the end, when with the loſſe of ſo much blood ſhe felt her death approach, liſting her eies to heauen, and holding vp her hands, ſhe yeelded thanks to God, whom ſhe named her force, her vertue, her patience, and her chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, beſeeching him to accept that bloud (which to obey his commaundement) ſhe then had ſhead in reuerence of Chriſt Ieſus his ſonne, whereby ſhe ſtedfaſtly beleeued all her ſins to be forgiuen, and ſaying, Lord receiue the ſoule that by thy mercie hath freely beene redeemed, ſhe fell with her face vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ground; and being fallen, the wicked villaine gaue her diuers blows; wherwith hauing loſt her ſpeech, and ſtrength of body failing, the villaine tooke by force that which ſhee for want of ſtrength could not defend. And hauing ſatiſfied his filthy luſt, fled ſo haſtily, that neuer after (what meanes ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer was wrought) he could be found. Meane time the young wench that lay with the Multiers wife, with feare crept vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the bed: but perceiuing the man to be gone, came out, and finding her miſtris to be without either ſpeech or feeling, ſhee cried at the window to the neighbors round about for helps, whereat ſuch as loued and liked her well came preſently vnto her, bringing Surgeons with them, and found ſhe had recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued fiue and twenty deadly wounds vpon hir body, which, as much as in them lay they ſought to heale; but all in vaine: neuertheleſſe, ſhee languiſhed without ſpeech in that ſort for the ſpace of one whole houre, mooued her handes, and eyes, whereby ſhe ſhewed not to haue loſt her memorie; and being by a prieſt examined of her faith, ſhee made thereof ſuch eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſigns, as that by word of mouth ſhe could not have done better, ſhewing that her truſt was in the death of Ieſus Chriſt, whom ſhe hoped ſhortly to behold within his heauenly ſeate: and ſo with a cheerefull countenance, her eies looking vp to heauen, ſhe yeelded her chaſte body vnto the earth, and her ſoule vnto the Lord: and being taken vp, and her bodie wownd and ſet before the doore, ſtaying for company to bring her to her graue, her huſband chaunced to come home, where
<pb facs="tcp:21446:11"/> he eſpied his dead wife ſtanding at the doore before he knewe thereof: and hauing inquired of the cauſe, had double reaſon to be grieued thereat, whereby he fell ſo ſicke, that hardly he eſcaped death. In this manner that martire of chaſtitie was buried in ſaint Florentines Church, whither all the honeſt wiues within the towne failed not to beare her company, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting themſelues moſt happy to be of ſuch a towne where ſo vertuous a woman was found: and therewith thoſe that were not ſo wiſe, but lighter of behauiour, ſeeing the honour done vnto that body, determined from that time forwardes to change their wicked liues.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="novel">
               <head>The third Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ A King of Naples abuſing a Gentlemans wife, in the end ware hornes himſelfe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ecauſe Gentlewomen (ſaide <hi>Saffredant)</hi> I have often wiſhed my ſelfe to be companion in the fortune of him, whereof I meane to ſpeake, I will ſhew you that in the cittie of Naples in the time of king <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> whoſe laſciuious life was his Scepter, there was a Gentleman ſo honeſt, faire and curteous, that by reaſon of his perfections an olde Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman gaue him his daughter in marriage, that for beautie and good grace was nothing inferior to him, who loued well together, vntill Shrouetide after, that the King in maſking went from houſe to houſe to ſport himſelfe, wherein eache man inforced themſelues, to honour him as they could: and when he came to the Gentlemans houſe, he was receiued and entertained much better than elſe-where, as well with ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, as with muſike, and the faireſt wife (in his mind) that euer he had ſeene, who after the banquet was doone, ſhee and her huſband ſang a ſong with ſo good grace, that it increaſed her beuty: wherwith the king perceiuing two perfections in
<pb facs="tcp:21446:12"/> one body, tooke not ſo much delight in their pleaſant voyces, as in deuiſing how to breake thaccord: but the difficultie he found, was, the great and perfect loue he ſaw to be in them, which made him heare that: paſſion in his minde as couertly as he could: but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe himſelfe, he cauſed certaine banquets to be made, for all the Ladies and Gentlewomen within the Citie of Naples, where the Gentleman and his wife were not forgotten. And becauſe a man is eaſily induced to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue whatſoeuer he ſeeth, it ſeemed the Gentlewomans eies promiſed him ſome good fortune, if the huſbands preſence were no hinderance thereunto: and to proue it, he ſent her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band for 15. dayes or three weekes on meſſage vnto Rome: who was no ſooner gone, but his wife that neuer had bin ſo long without his company, made exceeding ſorrow: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his abſence often viſited by the king, as time and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſerued, both with faire ſpeeches, preſents, and with gifts, ſhe was not onely comforted, but well content her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſhould ſtay longer: and before the three weekes ended, wherin he ſhould returne, ſhe waxed ſo amorous of the king, that ſhe was as much grieued at his comming againe, as ſhe had beene ſorrowefull for his going. And not to looſe the preſence of the king, they agreed, that when her huſband went into the country, ſhe would make it known to him, who ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by might aſſuredly come to her, and ſo ſecretly, that the man whome ſhe feared more than her owne conſcience, ſhould not he burt: in hope whereof this Gentlewoman was ioyfull, ſo that at her huſbands returne ſhe ſeemed very glad, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he heard that in his abſence, the king had often viſited his wife, yet he ſuſpected no ill, but in proces of time, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re ſo hardly to be couered, beganne by little and little to ſhew, in ſuch maner, that the huſband in thend doubted ſome deceit, keeping ſo good watch, that he was therof aſſured: but by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the feare he had of him, that did him iniury, he made no ſhew thereof, determining to diſſemble, as deſiring rather to liue in ſecret griefe than once to hazard his life for a women that had no loue in her. Neuertheleſſe, in that deſpight hee
<pb facs="tcp:21446:12"/> thought to yeelde the like vnto the king, if poſſibly he might: and knowing that oftentimes deſpight: maketh women doe more than loue, ſpecially ſuch as haue great heartes, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable mindes, he being in the queenes preſence was ſo bold to ſay vnto her, that it pittied him to ſee her not ſo well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the King as ſhee deſerued. Whereunto the Queene that knew the loue the king bare to his wife, anſwered him, and ſaid, I cannot both haue honor and pleaſure at one time, I know I haue the honour, but another reapeth the pleaſure, and ſhe that hath my pleaſure yet hath ſhe not my honour. He that perceiued ful wel why ſhe vttered that ſpeech, anſwered her and ſaide: Madam, your honour proceedes from birth, as being ſo nobly born, that any degree cannot augment your glory, but your highneſſe beutie, grace, and honeſtie, hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſo much pleaſure, that ſhe which taketh that from you that is your due, doth her ſelfe more wrong than you, for that for a certaine glorie, which turneth to ſhame, ſhee looſeth as much pleaſure as you or any Gentlewoman in this land can haue. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much Madam I wil tell you, that if the king would lay his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>owne aſide, I thinke he ſhould haue ſmal ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage at my hands to pleaſe a woman, being well aſſured hereof, that to conte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſo honeſt a perſon as your ſelf, it would be better for him that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were of my complexion. The queene laughing anſwered him &amp; ſaid, although the king my huſband be of more de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icate complexion than your ſelfe; yet it is the loue he be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>th m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> contenteth mee ſo well, that I preferre the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> before all other thinges. The Gentleman repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſaid: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, if it were ſo, you would not pittie me, for hereof am I aſſured, that the honeſt loue which reſteth in your heart would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> you more conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment, if it founde the like within the king; but God hath well prouided other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to them that you not finding that in him which you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, you ſhould not vſe him for your God on earth. I aſſure you, ſaid the Queene, the loue I beare him is ſo great, that in no woman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heart but mine the lik<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is to be found. Pardon me Mada<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (ſaid the Gentleman) you haue not yet well tried
<pb facs="tcp:21446:13"/> the loue of all mens hearts: for this I dare wel ſay, there is one that loueth you, whoſe loue is ſo importable, that yours in his reſpect is not to be compared; and for that he ſeeth the kings loue much quenched towards you, his doth ſo much in creaſe, that if you like thereof, you ſhalbe ſatiſfied for all your loſſes paſt. The Queene therewith beganne as wel by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward geſture, as by wordes, to finde his ſpeech proceeded from his heart: and calling to minde, that of long time her ſought to do her ſeruice, with ſuch affection, that hee wholie ſeemed melancholy, which ſhee eſteemed becauſe of his bad wife, but as then the ſtedfaſtly beleeued it was for the loue of her, as alſo the vertue of loue, which maketh it ſelfe felt not being done, aſſured her of that which no man elſe could tell: And beholding the Gentleman to be of greater beautie than the king, perceiuing him alſo cleane caſt off by his wife, as ſhe was of the king, being vrged with deſpite and ielouſie of her huſband, and mooued with the loue of the Gentleman, with teares ready to droppe out of her eies, ſighing ſhee ſpake and ſaid, O God! muſt reuenge of wrong work that in me, which loue could neuer do: Which the Gentleman hearing, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red her and ſaid: Madam the reuenge is eaſie to him, that in place of killing his enemy giueth life to a perfect friend: me thinketh it is time that truth ſhould take from you the fooliſh loue you beare to him that loueth you not againe; and that the iuſt and reaſonable loue ſhould driue that fear out of your mind, which neuer can remaine within a vertuous hart. Now Madam, let vs lay aſide the greatneſſe of your ſtate, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our ſelues to be the man and wife in this worlde, moſt mocked and betrayed of thoſe we dearely loued: let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge our ſelues (good Madam) not ſo much to giue them their deſert, as to ſatiſfie the loue which on my behalfe can no longer be forborue, vnles it coſt me my life: and this I think if your heart be not hardened more than a Diamond, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible you ſhould not feele ſome ſparke of fire which increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſo much more, as I ſeeke to couer it, if pity of me, which for your loue ſtil die, cannot mooue you to loue me, at leaſt,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:13"/> the loue of your owne ſelfe ſhould conſtraine you thereunto, who being ſo perfect, deſerue the hearts of all the honeſt Gentlemen in the world: being diſpiſed and forſaken of him, for whome you haue diſdained all the reſt.</p>
               <p>The queene hearing theſe words was therwith in ſuch a tranſe, that fearing once by countenance to ſhew hir troubled minde, and leaning on the Gentlemans arme, went into a Garden adioyning to her chamber, where ſhee walked long before that ſhe could vtter any word, but the gentleman per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauing her to be halfe wonne, being at the Allies end where no man could diſcouer what they did, ſhewd her by effect the loue he had ſo long conceald from her, &amp; finding themſelues to be of one conſent they tooke reuenge in that, whereof the paſſion ſeemed intollerable, and there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they did agree, that as often as he went into the Countrie, and the King into the Towne, he would not faile to come vnto the Caſtell to ſee the Queene, and in that maner deceiuing the deceiuers, they ſhuld be foure participants of that pleaſure which two alone thought onely to inioye: this agreement made, the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man returned home, and the Queene into her Chamber, with ſuch contented mindes, that all their former griefe was cleane conſumed, and the feare that each of them might haue of the Kings repaire vnto the gentlwoman, was wholy tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to deſire, which cauſed the gentleman oftener to go (then he had vſed) to his country houſe, being but halfe a mile from thence. Which the King no ſooner knew, but he went to ſee the gentlewoman: and the gentlman when night came went likewiſe to the Queene, as lieuetenant to the King ſo ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as it neuer could be ſpied: which life continued long, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the King, being no common perſon, could not ſo well diſſemble his loue, but that the world perceiued it full well, whereby all honeſt men tooke pitie of the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans eſtate in that ſome bad companions refrained not to mocke and ſcorne him, which he perceiued wel, where with he was ſo well content, that he eſteemed his hornes as much as the king eſteemed his crowne. Who on a time being with
<pb facs="tcp:21446:14"/> the Gentleman, could not refraine (ſeeing a harts head nai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp in the Gentlemans houſe) to ſmile before him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſuch a head became the houſe ful well. But the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in courage not inferior to the King, wrote ouer the head, ſaying, I beare theſe hornes as euery one may ſee, but ſome do beare them that beleeue it not. And when the king came thither againe, and found the ſame writing there, he aſked the gentleman the meaning thereof, who made him anſwer: if the kings ſecret be hidden from the heart, it is no reaſon why the harts ſhould be declared to the king: but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelfe (my Lord) ſaid he, that all thoſe which beare hornes go not bare head, for that they are thought, that they vncouer no man, and he beareth them lighteſt, that thinketh he hath none. The king knew wel by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe words that ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what was diſcouered, yet neuer ſuſpected the loue between the queene &amp; him: for that the more the queene contented her ſelfe with the kings behauior, ſo much the more ſhe ſeemed diſcontent, whereby long time they liued in that ſort, on all partes, vntill by age they were conſtrained to leaue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="novel">
               <head>The fourth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The raſh enterpriſe of a Gentleman towards a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of Flaunders, with the ſhame and diſcredite hee reaped thereby.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here dwelt in the country of Flaunders a Ladie of ſuch ſtate as better there could not be; a widow of two huſbands, by whom ſhe had no children, whereby during her widowhoode ſhee continued in her brothers houſe, of whom ſhe was well beloued, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great Lord and huſband to a kings daughter. This yong prince was much giuen vnto his pleaſure, louing hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſtimes, and company of Ladies, as youth requireth, hauing a wife ſo troubleſome and melancholy, that her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands
<pb facs="tcp:21446:14"/> pleaſures were no delight to her at al: wherefore the ſaid Lord ſtill deſired his ſiſters preſence, being a pleaſant Gentlewoman, and the beſt companion that might be found, yet very wiſe and of great honeſtie. There was in this great Lordes houſe a Gentleman, whoſe port, beautie, and good behauior ſurpaſſed al the reſt of his companions. This gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman perceiuing his Maiſters ſiſter to be a Gentlewoman addicted vnto mirth, and alwayes pleaſant, thought to aſſay, if moouing her with the choice of an honeſt friend would not offend her: which he did, but found contrary anſwere to her outward ſhew: and though her anſwer was ſuch as became an honeſt woman, and ſo great a Princeſſe, yet perceiuing him to be ſo faire, and courteous withall, ſhe eaſily forgaue his bold attempt, ſhewing by outward countenance not to be diſpleaſed with him, in ſpeaking vnto her; telling him neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, that her deſire was not that hee ſhoulde mooue her any more therein: which he promiſed to obſerue, thereby not to looſe the honor and contentment he receiued in darke ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to her. Neuertheleſſe in time his affection ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, that he cleane forgat his former promiſe, not that he ſought to hazard it by words (as hauing ouermuch, and ſore againſt his wil tried her wiſe deniall) but thinking if he could find her in ſome place conuenient, that ſhee beeing a widow, yong, luſty, and of good complexion, would poſſibly take pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of them both. Which to effect, he ſaide vnto his maiſter, that not far from his houſe, he ſhuld find good ſtore of game, and that if it pleaſed him to goe thither to hunt three or foure ſtags, in the month of Maie, he ſhould not finde ſo pleaſant ſport elſewhere. Which the Lord, as well for the loue hee bare vnto the Gentleman, as for the pleaſure he vſually took in hunting, agreed vnto: going vnto his houſe, which he found, not onely faire, but excellently furniſhed, as any Gentlemans within that country, where he lodged the lorde and his lady in one chamber, and in an other chamber right ouer againſt that he placed her whome hee loued better than himſelfe. The chamber being ſo wel hanged with arras, both
<pb facs="tcp:21446:15"/> round about and ouer head, and ſo well matted, that it was impoſſible once to perceiue a trap doore, vnder her bed that went downe into the chamber where his mother lay, beeing an olde Gentlewoman, and ſomewhat lame, who by reaſon of her cough, fearing to diſeaſe the Princeſſe that lay in the chamber ouer her, chaunged chambers with her ſonne: and euery night after ſupper this olde Gentlewoman brought comfets into the Princes chamber, whereat the Gentleman was aſſiſtant, who being welbeloued, and ſecret with her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was not excluded from her when ſhee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de her readie, or when ſhe went to bed, where ſtil he found occaſion to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment his loue, in ſuch manner, that one night after hee had kept the Princeſſe waking ſo long time, that ſhe being ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, cauſed him to retire, he went into his chamber: and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing put on his braueſt and beſt perfumd ſhirt he had, with a night coife ſutable thereto, it ſeemed vnto him (in looking on himſelfe) that not any Lady in the world could finde in her heart to refuſe his loue: wherefore perſwading with himſelfe a happy ſucceſſe, he went to bed, wherein he lay not long, by reſon of the great deſire &amp; hope he had to obtaine a far more honorable ſucceſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and hauing ſent his ſeruants forth, he roſe to ſhut the doore, liſtening if he could heare any ſtirring in the princes chamber; and being well aſſured that euery man was at reſt, meant to bring his long deſired trauaile to effect, by little and little letting downe the trap, which being ſo well trimmed and lined with cloth, made not any noyſe: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing doone, by the ſame way went into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inces chamber, and to her bed (who as then beganne to ſleepe) not once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membering the promiſe made vnto her, neither yet reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her high parentage, where without reuerence or once aſking leaue he lay downe by her, who ſoner felt her ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween his armes, then once perceiued his comming. But ſhe being ſtrong, vnloſed her ſelfe, and aſking what he was, began in ſuch ſort to ſtrike, bite, and ſcratch, that for the feare he had ſhe ſhould cry out he was conſtrained to couer her mouth, which neuertheleſſe he could not doe, ſo that when
<pb facs="tcp:21446:15"/> ſhe perceiued he ſpared not all meanes to force her to his wil, ſhe ſpared not againe to keep him from it, calling her waiting gentlewoman as loud as poſſible ſhe could, that ſlept within her chamber, &amp; an old &amp; vertuous lady as any could be found who in her ſmocke came ſtrait vnto her miſtris. But when the gentleman perceiued himſelfe diſcouered, hee was in ſo great feare to be knowne vnto the lady, that in as great haſte as he could he got down by the trap, and ſo with as much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and hope as before he had to be receiued, with much more feare and deepe diſpaire he was glad to goe away; and tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his glaſſe in hand, hauing a candle vpon the table, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held his face by her all bloody, ſcratched, and bitten, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the blood ranne downe vpon his ſhirt, in ſuch maner, that it appeared more bloody than wrought with gold. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he ſaid: O beuty, thou now haſt wonne thy iuſt reward, for by thy vaine promiſe, I haue enterpriſed a thing impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which in lieu of increaſing my deſire, may be a ſtrong re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubling of my griefe: being well aſſured, that if ſhe once do perceiue that contrary to my promiſe I haue enterpriſed this folie, I ſhal not only leeſe my honeſtie, but the daily frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with her, that more than others. I vſually haue hade that which my glory, beuty, &amp; good grace hath wel deſerued, I ought not once to couer; but to obtaine her loue, I ſhoulde not ſo haue ventured, to force her chaſte and princely body, but rather by true ſeruice, &amp; humble patience attend the time when loue might be victorious, becauſe that without it al the vertues, &amp; forces of man can naught auaile. In which ſort he paſſed the night in tears, ſighs &amp; griefs vnpoſſible to reherſe: &amp; in the morning perceiuing his face al mangled, he fained to be ſicke, and not able to indure the light til al the company was gone. The Lady that had wonne the victorie, knowing, that not any man in her brothers houſe, durſt once attempt ſo bad an enterpriſe, but onely he that had ſo boldly opened his loue vnto her, perſwaded her ſelfe aſſuredly it was her hoſte: and hauing with her Gentlewoman ſought round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the chamber, to ſee if they coulde finde him: in a great
<pb facs="tcp:21446:16"/> rage ſhe ſaid, Aſſure your ſelfe this is not doont but onelie by the maiſter of the houſe; but in the morning I wil ſo deale with my Lord my brother, that with his head hee ſhall wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe my chaſtitie. Which his furie the gentlewoman per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, ſaid: Madam, I much reioyce at the great care you haue vnto your honour, which to augment, you woulde not ſpare the life of him, that by the force of loue hath hazarded himſelfe, but oftentimes there are ſuch as ſeeke to increaſe it, to the contrary do diminiſh it: wherefore Madam I beſeech you not to diſcloſe the trueth. And when the Princeſſe had tolde her how it happened, the Gentlewoman ſaid vnto her: Your Ladiſhip aſſureth me that he obtained naught of you but blowes and ſcratches. Of that I aſſure you ſaid ſhe, and in ſuch manner, that if he found not a good ſurgeon, I think the markes will eaſily appeere. Madam, ſeeing it is ſo, ſaid the Gentlewoman, mee thinketh you haue more occaſion to praiſe God, than to think on your reuenge: for you may well ſuppoſe that, ſeeing he had ſo good courage to enterpriſe ſuch a thing, than the deſpight he hath receiued in failing thereof, you cannot giue him any death, that would not be much eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er vnto him. If you deſire to be reuenged on him, let loue and ſhame worke which knowe howe to torment him better than your ſelfe, and doe it for your honour; beware Madam I ſay to fall into the like; for that in lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to obtaine the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt pleſure that he could deuiſe, he hath receiued the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme diſpleſure that any gentleman can haue. And you ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, thinking to increaſe your honor, may thereby diminiſh it: and by making complaint thereof, make that known, that neuer was knowne before: for by him you may be wel aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it neuer ſhalbe reuealed: and ſay my Lorde your brother ſhould do that iuſtice you require, and therby the poore gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman looſe his life; yet the common voyce would be, that he had his pleaſure of you; and againe men would not ſticke to ſay, It is impoſſible for a gentleman to enterpriſe ſuch a thing, vnleſſe the Lady haue giuen him great occaſion. You are both yong and faire, liuing merrily in companies: there
<pb facs="tcp:21446:16"/> is not any man in the Court but ſeeth wel what fauour you ſhew to him whome you ſuſpect, which will make all men iudge, that if he hath enterpriſed ſuch a thing, it was not done without ſome fault committed on your behalfe. And your Honour, which hitherto hath made you hold your head aloft, ſhall by that meanes be brought in queſtion whereſoeuer it ſhal be knowne. The Princeſſe hearing the good reaſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by her gentlewoman, knew well ſhe ſaide the truth, and that with good reaſon ſhee ſhoulde bee blamed, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the priuate and good countenance ſhe had alwayes ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen vnto the gentleman, aſked her what ſhe were beſt to do, who anſwered her, and ſaid: madame, ſeeing it pleaſeth you to heare councell, perceiuing from what affection it proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, me thinkes you ſhould be merry at your hart to ſee, that the faireſt and honeſteſt gentleman that euer I knew, could neither by loue nor force, make you diſhoneſt your ſelfe. Wherein madame, you ought to thanke God, acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it not to be doone of your ſelfe, for that many women, leading farre more ſtricter liues then you, haue been ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and vanquiſht by men leſſe worthy to be loued then he: and you ought now more then euer to abſtaine from hearing any diſcourſes of loue, bicauſe many there are, which hauing anoyded the firſt occaſion, yet in the ſecond could not reſiſt. Remember good madame, that loue is blind, and blindeth men in ſuch ſort, that where men thinke the way to be moſt ſure, there commonly their feet doe ſooneſt ſlip. And me thinketh madam that you ought neither vnto him nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make it knowne, and though he would remember you thereof, yet make you as though you knewe it not, thereby to auoide all dangers that enſue, the one of vaine glory, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the victory you haue had, the other in calling thinges to mind that are ſo pleaſant to the fleſh, that moſt chaſte per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haue much to do to keep themſelues from ſome ſparks thereof, although they ſhunne them as much as in them lieth. And further (Madam) to the end he ſhall not thinke that he hath hazarded a thing which might content or pleaſe you: I
<pb facs="tcp:21446:17"/> am of this opinion, that by little and little you ſhal withdraw the good countenaunce you haue vſed towardes him, to the end he may perceiue how much you diſlike of that his follie, and how great your goodnes is, in contenting your ſelf with the victory that God hath giuen you, without requiring fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reuenge of him. And I beſeech God madam (ſaid ſhe) giue you the grace to continue the honeſtie hee hath put into your heart; and knowing that all goodneſſe commeth from him, you may loue and ſerue him better than euer you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. The princeſſe therewith determined to folow her Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlewomans counſell, and thereupon ſlept with as quiet and glad a mind, as the gentlman to the contrary waked in great diſpaire. The next day the Lord would ride away, and aſke for his hoſt, who was certified he was ſo ſicke that hee could not indure to ſee the light, or ſpeake to any man; whereat the prince was much abaſhed, and woulde haue ſeene him, but knowing he tooke his reſt, would not diſeaſe him, &amp; ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bidding him farewell, departed from his houſe, taking both his wife and his ſiſter with him: who vnderſtanding the gentlemans excuſe, that would not ſee the prince, nor yet his company before they went, was well aſſured it was he that ſo had troubled her, not daring to ſhew the marks ſhe had ſet vpon his face: and although his maiſter ſent often for him, yet would he not returne vnto the Court, before hee had per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly healed all his wounds, except that onely which loue and deſpight had made within his heart. But when he went vnto the prince, and that he found himſelfe before his victorious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, he could not chuſe but bluſh; and he that of all others had bin moſt aduenturous, was ſo aſtoniſhed, that ofttimes in her preſence he was abaſhed, whereby ſhe aſſured her ſelfe their ſuſpition to be true, and by litle and litle eſtranged her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from him, not ſo couertly, but he perceiued it well, yet durſt not be ſeene therein, fearing to haue worſe, and kept his loue within his heart, with the patience of withdrawing it, which he had well deſerued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="novel">
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:17"/>
               <head>The fift Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ Of a Watermans wife that eſcaped from two Friers that woulde haue forced her, and wrought in ſuch maner, that their fact was diſcouered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T the port of Cullen hard by Nyort, there was a woman that both night and day did continualy beare men ouer the water, wher it happened two friers to paſſe ouer in her beat, and no other company with them: and for becauſe that it is one of the longeſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in Fraunce, to the ende they might keepe her from wearineſſe, they mooued her with loue, wherein ſhe anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them as ſhe ought to doe. But they not being wearie of the way, neither yet by reaſon of the coldnes of the water, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olde, nor at the womans deniall once ſeemed aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, each of them determined to force her, and if ſhee cried out, to caſt her into the riuer: but ſhe being as wiſe and ſuttle as they malicious fooles, ſpake vnto them, and ſaide: I am not altogether ſo vncurteous, as outwardly I ſhew; but firſt I would deſire you to graunt me two requeſts, which done, you ſhall well perceiue that I haue better wil to obey you than you deſire. With that the friers ſwore vnto her by their good S. Frauncis, that whatſoeuer ſhee aſked of them ſhee ſhould bee ſure to obtaine, ſo they might haue their deſires. Firſt then ſaid ſhe, I wil haue you ſweare and promiſe me of your faiths, neuer to make it knowne to any man but your ſelues, which they willingly yeelded vnto: and then ſhe ſaid that they ſhould take their pleaſures one after an other, for that ſaid ſhe I ſhould be much aſhamed that any man ſhould looke vpon me while I did it, wherefore ſaide ſhe, caſt lottes betweene you who ſhal firſt begin. They ſaw her requeſts ſo reaſonable, the yonger frier conſented that the elder ſhuld be firſt, and aproching neere an Iland ſhe ſaid vnto the yonger, Pray you here in this Iland till I haue carried your fellowe into an other Iland, and if at his returne hee doe like well
<pb facs="tcp:21446:18"/> of me, we wil leaue him here, and goe to an other place with you. Wherewith the yonger Frier leapt into the Iſland, ſtaying the returne of his companion, whome the woman brought into another, &amp; being at the ſhore, making as though ſhe tied the boat, ſayde vnto him: Friend, looke what place we were left to go into, wherewith the good father ſtept into the Iſland, to finde conuenient place, and he was no ſooner on land, but ſhe giuing a thruſt with her foote againſt a tree, made her boate to giue backe into the riuer, leauing the two holy fathers in the Iſles, to whom ſhe cried as loud as euer ſhe could, and ſayde: Stay there my maſters till God ſende his holy Angell to comfort you, for of mee, as this day, you get not any thing that may content you. The two poore fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers perceiuing her deceit, kneeled downe vpon the ſhore, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring her not to diſcredite them, promiſing her, if that ſhee would cary them to the hauen, they woulde not trouble her: but ſhe rowing on, ſayd vnto them: I might well be counted a foole, hauing eſcaped your hands, to put my ſelfe into your dangers againe. Which done, returning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> village, ſhe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her huſband &amp; the officers, deſiring them to helpe to take two great deuouring wolues, from whom (by Gods helpe) ſhee had eſcaped. They being well accompanied, went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for that neither great nor little within the village, but was deſirous to bee partaker of that ſport. The two poore friers perceiuing ſo great a company comming to them, hid themſelues in the Iſles (like Adam from the preſence of God) ſhame ſetting their ſinnes before their eyes, and feare of puniſhment made them ſo tremble, that in a maner they were halfe dead. But that kept them not from being taken and led to priſon, not without great ſhouting &amp; crying of the people: ſome ſaying, theſe good fathers preach chaſtity vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, yet would defile our wiues: and her huſband ſayde, they dare not handle money, and yet will handle our womens thighes, which are more dangerous. Others ſayd, they are ſepulchres all beautified without, and inwardly filled with dead and rotten diſeaſes. And others cried, and ſayde, that
<pb facs="tcp:21446:18"/> by their fruites men might perceiue what trees they were. So that you muſt beleeue that all the paſſages which are found to be in the holy Scriptures againſt hypocrites, were alledged againſt thoſe poore priſoners, that by the gardiens meanes were ſuccoured and deliuered: who in great haſte came thither to fetch them, aſſuring the officers, that hee would vſe greater iuſtice againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then the ſecular Iudge could do. And to ſatiſfie the partie, he proteſted they woulde ſay as many prayers for her as ſhe would deſire: whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Iudge granted him his requeſt, and deliuered him the priſoners, that were ſo well ſchooled by the gardien (being an honeſt man) that neuer after they paſſed ouer the riuer without making the ſigne of the holy croſſe, and commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="novel">
               <head>The ſixt Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The ſubtiltie of a woman, that found meanes to let her friend eſcape, when her husband (hauing but one eie) thought to ſurpriſe him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here was an olde ſeruaunt of the chamber to <hi>Charles</hi> laſt duke of Alonſon, that had loſt one of his eies, and was maried to a woman much yonger then himſelfe, he being by his maſter and miſtreſſe as well beloued as any man of his eſtate could be, whereby he had not meanes to viſite his wife ſo oft as willingly he woulde, which was the cauſe that ſhe forgot both honour and conſcience, and fell in loue with a yong Gentleman, which in fine was ſo well knowen, that at length her huſband was aduertiſed: which he would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, by reaſon of the great and outward ſignes of loue his wife did ſhew vnto him. Neuertheleſſe, one day thinking to finde it out, and if he coulde, to be reuenged on him that did him wrong, he fained to goe into the countrey not farre from thence, where he ſayde, he muſt ſtay at the leaſt two or three dayes. He being gone, his wife ſent for her man, but he had not beene with her aboue halfe an houre, when her huſbande
<pb facs="tcp:21446:19"/> came againe, and in great haſte knocked at the doore, which the perceiuing, tolde her friend, whereat he was ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſht, that hee wiſht himſelfe in his mothers belly, and curſt both her, and loue, that had brought him to that danger: ſhe bade him take no thought, ſaying ſhe would finde meanes to let him goe without ſhame or harme, willing him with all ſpeed to make him ready. Meane time the huſband knocked ſtill at the doore, and called his wife as loud as euer he could, but ſhe counterfeiting as if ſhe knew him not, ſayde vnto her ſeruant, why doe you not riſe, and make them leaue their noiſe, that knocke and call ſo haſtily at the doore: is this a time of night to come and knocke at honeſt mens doores? if my huſband were here, he would make you leaue. The huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band hearing his wife ſpeake, called her as loud as he could, and ſayd, Wife, open the doore: will you let me ſtand heere till it be day? And when ſhe ſaw her friend was ready to go out, opening the doore, ſhe ſayde vnto her huſband: Oh huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, how glad am I that you are come; for I had a ſtrange dreame, wherewith I was ſo well pleaſed, as poſſible might be, becauſe I dreamt that you had recouered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of your other eye, and with that imbracing and kiſſing him, ſhe tooke him by the head, and with one of her handes ſtopping his good eye, aſked him, doe you not ſee better then you were woont to doe? and while he coulde not ſee at all, ſhe let her friend go out. Whereof her huſband doubted, and ſayd: By God wife, I will neuer watch you againe, for that in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deceiue you, I haue found the fineſt ſubtiltie that euer was inuented. God amend you, for it is not in the power of any man liuing, to preuent the malice of a woman, vnleſſe he kill her. But ſeeing the good enterteinment you haue had at any handes, coulde not procure you to amend, it may be, my abſence will force you thereunto. Which ſayd, he went his way, and left his wife in great diſcomfort, who by meanes of his kinſemen, friendes excuſes, and teares, was of him receiued againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="novel">
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:19"/>
               <head>The ſeuenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ A marchant of Paris deceiued the mother of his loue, to couer their fault.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the citie of Paris there was a marchant that loued a mayde that dwelt hard by him, or to ſay the trueth, better loued of her, then ſhe of him: for that the ſhew he made to loue her, was but to couer a more honourable &amp; haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie loue then hers. But ſhe that was content to be deceiued, loued him ſo well, that ſhe had wholly forgotten the maner that women ought to vſe, in refuſing men. This crafty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, after he had long time taken paines to goe to her, in the end made her ſo fond, that ſhee ranne after him: which her mother, being an honeſt woman, perceiuing, wholly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade her the company of that marchant, which if ſhee obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued not, ſhe ſayd ſhee would place her in a religious houſe. But the daughter that loued the marchant more then ſhee feared her mother, made more of him then euer ſhe did: and one day being in a chamber alone, the marchant went in, who finding place conuenient, ſpake as ſecretly vnto her as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly he might, but a certeine mayd ſeeing him going in, went and tolde her mother, who in great cholar ranne thither: and when her daughter heard her come, ſhee wept vnto the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant, and ſayd, Alas my loue, now the loue I beare vnto you, ſhalbe dearely bought, here comes my mother who will ſurely know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which ſhe alwayes feared. The marchant that therwith was not abaſht, left her preſently, and went to meet her mother, and opening his armes, imbraced her as hard as euer he could, and with the ſame fury wherewith he vſed the daughter, he threw the poore olde woman vpon a bed, who found that maner of enterteinment to be ſo ſtrange, that ſhe knew not what to do, but onely to ſay, what will you haue? what are you madde? but for all that he left not off to handle
<pb facs="tcp:21446:20"/> her in ſuch ſort as if ſhe had beene the faireſt mayde in all the world: and had it not beene that ſhee cried ſo loud, that both her men and mayds came in to helpe, ſhe had paſt the ſame way which ſhe ſo much feared for her daughter. Wherefore by maine ſtrength they tooke the poore olde woman out of the marchants armes, without once knowing, nor yet could euer know, the cauſe wherefore he vſed her ſo. Meane time her daughter got into another houſe, wherein there was a wedding, which time the marchant and ſhee did often call to minde, and laughed thereat, but to the olde wiues coſt, that neuer could perceiue it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="novel">
               <head>The eight Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ A certeine man hauing lien with his wife, thinking ſhe had bene his mayde, ſent his companion thither, that made him cuckolde, his wife not knowing thereof.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the countie of Aller, there was a man called Bornet, that had married an honeſt woman, whoſe credit and reputation he loued, as all the huſbands that are heere in place (as I thinke) do, and although he deſired his wife ſhoulde be faithfull vnto him, yet hee woulde not that the lawe (in that caſe) ſhoulde be equall to them both: for that hee became a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous of his mayde, in which exchange he feared nothing, but that diuerſitie of meats would not pleaſe him. He had a neighbour, of one condition, named Sandras, both a Drum maker and a Taylor, betweene whom there was ſo great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliaritie, that their wiues onely excepted, their goods were in a manner common: whereupon hee ſhewed his friend the enterpriſe he meant to make vpon his mayde, who not onely liked it well, but to his power holpe to bring it to paſſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to haue ſome ſhare therein. The mayd that would not conſent thereto, perceiuing her ſelfe ſo hardly followed,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:20"/> ſhewed to her miſtreſſe, deſiring her to giue her leaue to goe vnto her friends, ſaying ſhe could not liue in that ſort. The miſtreſſe that loued her huſband well, whom ſhe did ſuſpect, being very glad to haue occaſion thereby iuſtly to charge him, ſayd vnto her mayde, content your ſelfe, and holde my huſband with faire words, and in the end appoint him to lie with you, but faile not at any hand to tell me certeinly the night when the ſame ſhall be, and take heede that no man knowes it. The mayd did as her miſtreſſe had commanded, which pleaſed her maſter ſo well, that hee went to tell his friend, who deſired him, that ſeeing he had bene a partner in making the match, he might likewiſe haue ſome part of that he left. The promiſe made, and the time come, the maſter went to bed (as he thoght) with his maid, but ſhe that had as then renounced the authoritie of commaunding, for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be a ſeruant, had layde her ſelfe in the mayds bed, and receiued her huſband therein, not as a wife, but rather ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a baſhful mayd, and in ſuch maner, that her huſband could neuer perceiue it. I cannot tell you which of them was beſt pleaſed, whether he in thinking to deceiue his wife, or ſhe to deceiue her huſband: but when he had beene with her, not ſo long as pleaſed him, but as he found himſelfe able to beare it out, being not altogether ſo ſtout a warrier, as otherwiſe he had bene, he roſe and went out of the houſe, where finding his companion ſtronger and yonger then himſelfe, tolde him that he had found the beſt gown that euer he ſaw. You know ſayd his companion, what you promiſed me. Go then quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſayd the maſter, leſt ſhe ſhould riſe, or that my wife ſhould call her for ſome buſineſſe. His companion went thither, and found the ſame mayd there which the huſband had miſtaken, who thinking him to be her huſband, refuſed not whatſoeuer he would aſke: I meane by aſking, taking, for he durſt not ſpeake. And there he ſtayed longer then the huſband did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: whereat the woman wondred, for ſhe was not woont to haue ſuch kinde of nights: neuertheleſſe, ſhee was content, comforting herſelfe with the ſpeeches which in the morning
<pb facs="tcp:21446:21"/> ſhe meant to vſe vnto him, and with the mockerie. About breake of day the man roſe vp, and in departing from her, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpoſed to play, by chance hee tooke a ring from off her finger, which ring her huſband gaue her when they married: (a thing which the women of that countrey do keepe in great ſolemnitie, and honour much that woman which keepeth her ring vntill ſhe dies: and to the contrary, if ſhe chance to loſe it, ſhe is diſcredited, as hauing giuen her faith vnto another man beſides her huſband) ſhee was content that he ſhoulde take it, thinking that it would ſerue for a certeine token of his late deceit. When the companion returned againe, he aſked him, what he had done, and how he liked the match: he tolde him he was of his opinion, and that if he had not feared day, he had not come as yet, wherewith as ſoftly as they could they went to bed. In the morning, as he made him ready, the huſband perceiued the ring which his companion ware vpon his finger, in all points like to that which he had giuen his wife when they were married; wherewith hee aſked his companion of whom he had it: but when he vnderſtood he had ſnatcht it from the mayd, he was abaſht, and began to leane his head againſt the wal, and ſaid: Good God, haue I made my ſelfe cuckolde, my wife not knowing it? his companion to comfort him, ſpake &amp; ſayd, It may be, your wife when ſhe went to bed, gaue your mayde the ring to keepe. With that the huſband went into the houſe, where he found his wife, fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, finer, and merrier then vſually ſhe had beene, as ſhe that much reioyced to haue ſaued the conſcience of her mayd, and tried her huſband euen to the full, with no more loſſe then watching for a night. The huſband perceiuing her to ſeem ſo pleaſant, ſayd within himſelfe: If ſhe knew my fortune, ſhe would not looke ſo merrily vpon me: and ſpeaking vnto her of diuers things, he tooke her by the hand, and perceiuing ſhe had not the ring, which ſhe neuer put off her finger, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſo much abaſht, that with a trembling voice, he aſked her and ſayd, What haue you done with your ring? but ſhe that was full glad that he began to mooue that which ſhe her
<pb facs="tcp:21446:21"/> ſelfe deſired to vtter, ſayd vnto him: O the moſt wicked man that euer liued on the earth, from whome thinke you, you tooke the ring? you thought you tooke it from my mayd, for whoſe ſake you haue ſpent double ſo much more of your good neſſe, then euer you did for mee: for the firſt time that you came to me, I eſteemed you ſo amorous of her, that more you could not be, but after you went out, and then came in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, you ſeemed to be a deuill, and not a man; O vnhappy wretch; thinke with your ſelfe what blindneſſe hath bewitched you, ſo much to vſe my company whereof you haue receiued the pleaſure, and yet eſteemed it not. It is not then the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or perſon of your mayd that made you finde ſuch pleaſure at this time; but it is ſinne and filthy luſt that burneth in your heart, and makes your head ſo madde, that you had taken a goate at that time for a wench. Now huſband, it is time to mend your life, and content your ſelfe with me, knowing me to be your owne, and an honeſt woman, and thinke what you haue done, ſuppoſing me to be your chamber mayd: that I haue done was onely to withdraw from you ſinne, to the end that in our age, we both may liue in loue, with quiet conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. For if you meane to liue as you haue done, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeparate my ſelfe, then dayly to beholde the deſtruction of your ſoule, your body, and your goods before my face. But if you will confeſſe your fault, and purpoſe now to liue in godly ſort, obeying him, I will forget all former faults, as I beſeech the Lord to pardon my ingratitude, in not louing him as I ought. If euer man was abaſht, and in deſpaire, ſurely it was this man, perceiuing his wife ſo faire, ſo chaſte and honeſt, to haue bene left by him, for one that loued him not, and which is worſe, to haue bene ſo accurſt, to haue made her do amiſſe, not knowing it, and made another partaker of that pleaſure that onely was for him, whereby he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to weare the hornes, to his perpetuall ſhame. But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing his wife ſo moued, touching the loue he bare vnto the mayde, was well aduiſed not to diſcloſe the wicked touch he had playd with her, but aſking her forgiueneſſe, with promiſe
<pb facs="tcp:21446:22"/> to forgoe his wicked life, he gaue her the ring againe, which he had taken from the other man, whome he beſought not to diſcloſe the fact. But diuers thinges are ſpoken ſecretly that after come to light: for not long time after the trueth thereof was knowne, and he was called cuckold, without diſgrace to her.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="novel">
               <head>The ninth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The pitifull death of an amorous Gentleman, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouer late receiued comfort, from the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man whom he loued.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etweene Daulphinois and Prouance there was a Gentleman much richer in vertue, beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and honeſtie, than of worldly goods, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely loued a Gentlewoman, whoſe name I wil not now rehearſe, for her kinred ſake, that are proceeded of great and rich houſes; but aſſure your ſelues the thing is moſt true: and becauſe hee was not of the like houſe, he durſt not diſcouer his affection, for that the extreme loue he bare vnto her was ſo great and ſo perfect, that he had rather die than to deſire any thing that might haue beene to her diſhonour, and perceiuing himſelfe to be of ſo meane pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage in reſpect of hers, was wholy out of hope to marrie her. Wherefore his loue was grounded vpon no other point, than onelie to loue her with all his power, as perfectly as he could: which he ſo long continued, that in the end ſhe hadde ſome inkling thereof; and perceiuing the loue hee bare vnto her, ſo ful of vertue and good ſpeeches, ſhe eſteemed herſelfe moſt happy to be beloued of one that was ſo vertuous, and gaue him thereupon ſo good countenaunces, that hee which ſought no other thing, was there with well pleaſed. But ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice the enemy of all quietnes, could not indure this honeſt and happy life, for that certaine men ſaide vnto the mother of the gentlewoman, that they were much abaſhed what that gentleman made ſo much within her houſe, and that it was
<pb facs="tcp:21446:22"/> thought her daughters beautie was the onely cauſe, with whome he was often ſeene to ſpeake. The mother which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing doubted of the gentlemans honeſt behauiour, whereof ſhe aſſured herſelfe, as much as of any of her owne children, was very ſorie to heare that it was taken in euil part, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that in the ende (fearing ſome ſlaunder by malitious heades might thereby ariſe) deſired him for a time not to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent her houſe, as vſually hee had doone: a thing which hee found very hard to be viſgeſted, knowing that the honeſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches hee had vſed to her daughter deſerued no ſuch cauſe of abſence. Neuertheleſſe, to the end he might ceaſe euill ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, he forbare for ſo long time, and at laſt returned thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe, as he had done before, whoſe abſence had not diminiſhed his goodwill. But being in the houſe, hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode they meant to marry the Gentlewoman with a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who in his opinion was not ſo rich, that hee ſhould doe him ſuch wrong, to haue his loue, no more thou he himſelfe. And thereupon beganne to take heart, and to employ his friends to ſpeake for him; thinking that if the choiſe were put vnto the gentlewoman, ſhe would preferre him before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: neuertheleſſe, the mother of the gentlewoman and her friends, becauſe the other was richer, choſe him; where at the gentleman was ſo much diſpleaſed, that knowing his friend loſt as much contentment as himſelfe, by little and litle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other ſickenes, beganne to conſume, and in ſhort ſpace was changed, and that in ſuch ſort, that it ſeemed hee couered the beauty of his face, with the maſke of death, whereunto from hower to hower he ſtill approched: yet could he not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine, but ſometimes went to ſpeake with her whom he ſo deerely loued. But in the ende when ſtrength failed him, be was conſtrained to keepe his bed, whereof he would not once aduertiſe her whome he loued, fearing to procure her cauſe of griefe, and ſo ſuffering himſelfe to fall into deſpaire, he loſt both his eating, drinking and his naturall reſt, in ſomuch that it was impoſſible to know him by reaſon of his leanenes and ſtrange countenance. By chance a friend of his aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed
<pb facs="tcp:21446:23"/> the mother, of his loue who being very charitable, and on the otherſide loued the Gentleman ſo well, as that if all the friends had beene of her and her daughters opinion, they had preferd his honeſt behauiour before all the riches of the other Gentleman: but the fathers kindred would not conſent thereto. Shee with her daughter went to viſit him, whome ſhe found rather dead then liuing, and knowing his death to approch, had confeſſed himſelfe, and received the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thinking preſently to die and never to ſee any man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: but being as it were within two fingers breadth neere to death, ſeeing her that was his life and reſurrection, felt himſelfe ſo ſtrong that he caſt himſelfe vpon a bed ſaying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lady, what occaſion hath brought you hither Madame to come and viſit him that hath his foote already in the graue, and of whoſe death you are the cauſe? what (ſaid the Lady) may it be poſſible that he whom we loue ſo well, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue his death by our meanes? I pray you ſhewe vs for what cauſe you vſe this ſpeech? Madame ſaid he, although as much as in me lay, I haue diſſembled the loue I beare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Gentlewoman your daughter, ſo it is that my friends ſpeaking of her mariage &amp; mine together, haue ſpoken more then willingly I would, conſidering the miſchiefe that is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len vpon me, to looſe the hope, not for my particular pleaſure, but becauſe I know full well ſhee ſhall not be ſo wel vſed, nor ſo well beloved as ſhee ſhould haue beene with me. The good I perceiue ſhee looſeth of the beſt and moſt affectionat ſervant and friend that ſhee hath in this world, procureth me more grief, then the loſſe of this my life, which for her only I would preſerue, but ſeeing it can ſerue her to no end, in loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, it is to me great profit. The mother and the daughter hearing his diſcourſe, ſought by all meanes to comfort him. The mother ſaying vnto him, be of good courage and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you of my faith, that if God ſend you your health, my daughter ſhall never haue other huſband then your ſelfe, and here ſhee is in preſence, whom I command to giue her faith vnto you, The daughter weeping, laboured to do that which
<pb facs="tcp:21446:23"/> her mother promiſed ſhee ſhould: but he knowing that when he ſhould be whole, he ſhould not haue his loue, and that the good ſpeech ſhee vttered vnto him, was onely but to prooue if that ſhee could reviue him. Once againe he ſaid vnto her, that if thoſe words had beene ſpoken vnto him three months before, he had beene the healthfulleſt and the happieſt Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in France, but the reliefe came now ſo late, that it could not be beleeved, nor yet hoped, and when he ſawe they inforced themſelues to make him to beleeue it, he ſaid vnto them: Well ſeeing I perceiue you promiſe me that good which never wil come to paſſe, although you deſire it ſhould; for the weaknes wherein I am, I craue of you, a thing much leſſe then that, which hitherto I neuer was ſo bold for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: with that, both of them ſware to grant it bidding him freely ſpeake. I beſeech you then ſaid he, that you will giue her into my armes, whom you doe promiſe me ſhall bee my wife, and command her to imbrace and kiſſe me. The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that neuer had vſed any ſuch entertainement, thought to denie it him: but her mother commanded her expreſſely, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing there was no more liuely feeling in him, then in a dead man. Therewith the daughter by her mothers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement went to the ſicke mans bed, and ſaid vnto him, my good friend, I pray you comfort your ſelfe. The poore languiſhing Gentleman as well as he could in his extreame weakenes, ſtretched forth his armes, nothing but ſhinne and bones, and with all the ſtrength of his body imbraced the cauſe of that his death, and kiſſing hir with his pale and cold lippes, held her as long as poſſible he could, and then ſaide vnto her, the loue I haue borne vnto you hath beene ſo great and honeſt, that neuer (mariage ſet apart) did I deſire other fauour at your hands, then I haue nowe: for want whereof, and therewith I will moſt gladly yeeld my ſpirit vnto God, who is perfect loue and charity, and knoweth the greatnes of my loue, and my honeſt deſire beſeeching him (hauing my whole delight betweene mine armes) to receiue my ſpirit in his hands &amp; ſaying ſo, took her again into his armes ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:24"/> that the weake heart beeing not able to ſuſtaine that force, was wholy forſaken of all his liuely ſpirits, for that the ioie made it ſo to reioice, that the ſoule abandoning hir place, departed from the body, and although the poore body continued without life, and by that meanes coulde no more holde her griefe, neuertheleſſe the loue, which the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had alwaies hidden ſhewed it ſelfe ſo much at that time, that the mother and her ſeruants had much adoe to ſeperate their bodies. But by force pulled the liuing almoſt dead from the dead whom they cauſed honourably to be buried: but the greateſt triumph vſed at his obſequie was, the teares, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and cries of the poore Gentlewoman, which ſhewed ſo much the more after his death, as ſhee diſſembled them du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his life, in a maner ſatiſfying the wrong that ſhee had done vnto him, and ſince that time, (as I haue heard) what huſband ſoeuer ſhee had giuen her, ſhee was neuer merry at her heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="novel">
               <head>The tenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The incontinencie of a Duke, together with his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie to attaine his deſire, with the iuſt puniſhment of his euill intent.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong ſince there was a Duke of Florence, that had married the ladie Margaret baſtard daughter to the emperour Charles the fift: and becauſe as yet ſhe was ſo yong, that hee might not lie with her, ſtaying till ſhee came to yeares, he vſed her very kindly, for that to ſpare her he was amorous of certaine Ladies in the cittie, which by night he went to viſite, while his wife ſlept. Among others he loued a very faire, wiſe, and honeſt Gentlewoman, ſiſter to a Gentleman, of whome the Duke made great ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and to whom he gaue ſo great authoritie in his houſe, that his word was as much feared and obeied as if he had bin
<pb facs="tcp:21446:24"/> the Duke himſelfe: and there was no ſecret in his hart, that he made not knowne to him, in ſuch ſort that he might well be termed a ſecond Duke. The Duke perceiuing his ſiſter to be ſo honeſt, that by no meanes hee could declare his loue vnto her; after he had ſought all meanes he could, he went to the Gentleman, whome he loued ſo well, and ſaid vnto him: If there were anie thing in this world (my good friend ſaide he) that I would refuſe to do for you, I ſhould feare to ſhew you my deſire, and much more to intreate you to be aſſiſtant vnto me. But I beare ſuch loue vnto you, as that if I had either wife, mother, or daughter, that might be a meanes to ſaue your life, I would rather imploy them therein, than let you die for want of them. And I eſteeme the loue you beare to me, to be no leſſe, and in ſuch ſort, that if I my ſelfe which am your maiſter, do beare you ſuch affection, you can not at the leaſt beare leſſe to me. Wherefore I meane to vtter a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret vnto you, the ſecrecie whereof brings mee in ſuch a caſe as you now ſee, whereof I neuer hope redreſſe, but onelie by death, or by the ſeruice which in this reſpect you now may do vnto me. The Gentleman hearing his maiſters reaſons, and perceuing his face, vnfainedly wet with teares, took ſuch pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on him; that he ſaide vnto him: My Lord, al the good and honour I haue proceedes from you, you may ſpeake to me, as to your friend, being wel aſſured, that the thing which is in my power, is already in your handes. With that the Duke beganne to declare vnto him the loue he bare vnto his ſiſter, which was ſo great and ſtrong, as that if by his means he could not obtaine the ſame, he was not able to liue long, as knowing well that in regard of her, neither prayers nor preſents would ought preuaile, wherefore he deſired him, that if he loued his life, as much as he his, he would finde meanes to win him that fauour, which without him he neuer hoped for. The brother that loued his ſiſter, and the honour of his houſe, more then the Dukes pleaſure, ſought by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine reaſons to diſſwade him, beſeeching him to imploy him in any other thing rather than that, which might be ſo great
<pb facs="tcp:21446:25"/> a diſpight vnto him, as to purchaſe the diſhonor of his owne blood, ſaying that his heart and honour could not agree to do him ſeruice therein. The Duke inflamed with an inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able rage, put his finger in his mouth, biting his naile, and anſwered him in great fury, Well ſeeing I finde no friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in you, I know what I muſt do. The gentleman know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cruelty of his maſter, was in great feare, and ſaid vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him: My lord, ſeeing it is your pleaſure, I will ſpeake vnto her, and tell you what ſhe ſayth. The Duke anſwered, going from him, if you loue my life, I will likewiſe loue yours. The Gentleman vnderſtoode well what that word meant, and was a day or two before he ſaw the Duke againe, thinking what he had to doe: on the one ſide he ſet before his eyes the duety hee ought vnto his maſter, with the riches and honours that by his meanes hee had receiued, on the other ſide, the honour of his houſe, the honeſtie and chaſtitie of his ſiſter, whom he knew would neuer conſent to ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt an action, if by ſubtiltie ſhe were not deceiued, or by force compelled thereunto: a thing which he would finde ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange, ſeeing that thereby both he and his ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed. Wherefore he determined, that he had rather die, then commit ſo wicked a fact againſt his ſiſter, being one of the honeſteſt women in all Italie, and that he would rather deliuer his countrey of ſuch a tyrant, then by force to bring ſo great a ſhame vpon his owne houſe: for that he was aſſured, that without the Dukes death, his life, nor yet his friends could be in ſaftie: wherfore without ſpeaking to his ſiſter, he determined by one meanes to ſaue his owne life, and reuenge her ſhame, at the end of two dayes hee went vnto the Duke, and ſayd vnto him, that he had ſo well practiſed with his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (not without great paine) that in the end ſhe conſented to his will, vpon condition he ſhould keepe the thing ſo ſecret, that none but her brother ſhould know thereof. The Duke that deſired thoſe newes, beleeued him, and imbracing the meſſenger, promiſed him whatſoeuer he would deſire, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him to bring the ſame to paſſe with as much ſpeede as
<pb facs="tcp:21446:25"/> might be: whereupon they did appoint the day. If the Duke was glad, you need not doubt: and when he knew the night (hee ſo much deſired) to approch, wherein hee hoped to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the victorie of her, whome he eſteemed inuincible, he withdrew himſelfe with the Gentleman onely, not forgetting to put on his coife and perfumed ſhirt, the beſt that could be found. And when all were gone to reſt, hee went with the Gentleman vnto his houſe, where he entred into a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant chamber: there the Gentleman pulled off his night gowne, and layd him in his bed, ſaying vnto him, I will goe fetch her, that will not enter into this chamber without bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but I hope before morning, ſhe will be aſſured of you: with that hee left the Duke, and went into his chamber, where he found but one of his men, to whome he ſayd: Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou be ſo hardy to follow me vnto a place, where I will reuenge my ſelfe of the greateſt enemy I haue in all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. His man ignorant what he would do, ſayd: Sir, that I will, were it the Duke himſelfe. With that the Gentleman ledde him ſo ſuddenly that he had no other weapon then a poinard at his backe. When the Duke heard him come againe, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king he brought her with him whome he loued ſo well, he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the curtaines to ſee and receiue her, he had ſo long at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but in ſted of ſeeing her by whome he hoped the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of his life, he beheld his owne headlong falling into death, being a naked ſword which the gentlman had drawen, wherewith he ſtrake the Duke being in his ſhirt, who being deſtitute of armes, but not of hart, ſet himſelfe vpright with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bed and tooke the Gentleman by the middle, ſaying vnto him, Is this the promiſe you keepe? and ſeeing he had no other weapon but his teeth and nailes, he bit the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man by the thumb, &amp; by ſtrength of armes defended himſelfe ſo well, that both of them fell vpon the bed: the Gentleman beeing not well aſſured, called his ſeruant, who finding the Duke and his Maiſter ſo hardly elaſped togither, that hee knewe not which to chuſe, drewe them both by the feet into the middle of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> chamber, and with his ponyard aſſaied to
<pb facs="tcp:21446:26"/> eut the Dukes throate, who defended himſelfe vntill the loſſe of his bloud made him ſo weake that he could doe no more. Then the Gentleman and his ſeruant laide him in his bedde, where with the ſtabs of a dagger they made an end of killing him, and drawing their curten they went their waies, and ſhut the dead body within the chamber, and when he founde himſelfe victorious of his enemy, by whoſe death he hoped to ſet the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth at liberty, though his cruelty ſhould yet be imperfect, if he doe not as much to fiue or ſixe of thoſe that were the Dukes neereſt kinſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And to bring the ſame to paſſe, he ſaid vnto his ſervant that he would go and fetch them one after the other, to deale with them as he had done with the Duke: but his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t being neither ſtrong nor bold, ſaid vnto him, me thinketh ſir, you haue done enough at this time, and that you ſhall doe better in thinking howe to ſaue your owne life, then ſeeke to take it from others, for if wee ſtay ſo long to kill each of them, as we doe about the Duke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the day will ſooner diſcouer our enterpriſe, then wee ſhall bring it to an end, although we found out enemies without defence, the Gentleman, whoſe wicked conſcience made him fearefull beleeued his ſeruant, &amp; taking him with him, went vnto the Biſhop that had charge of opening the gates of the Citty, and to command the poſts and ſaid vnto him, I haue this night receiued news that a brother of mine is at the point of death, ſo that I haue deſired licence of the Duke to go vnto him, who hath granted it me, wherfore I pray you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the poſts to giue me two good horſes, and will the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to open me the gates. The Biſhop that eſteemed his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt no leſſe then the commandement of the Duke his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, gaue him preſently a billet, by vertue whereof the gate was opened vnto him, and the horſes deliuered according to his deſire, and inſteed of going to ſee his brother, he went to Venice, where hee cauſed the bytings he had receiued by the Duke to be healed, and from thence went into Turquie. In the morning the Dukes ſeruants ſeeing him ſo long before he came, ſuſpected he was gone to ſee ſome Gentlewoman,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:26"/> but perceiuing him to ſtay, began on al ſides to ſeeke him out. The poore Dutches that began to loue him wel, knowing he could not be found, was in great feare: but when the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman he loued ſo well, could no more be found then he, they went to ſeeke him at his houſe, &amp; finding bloud at his cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber dore, entered into the chamber, but no man could tel them newes, and following the teares of the bloud, the Dukes poore ſeruants came to the chamber wherein he was, which they found lockt, but they ſoone brake downe the dore: and perceiuing the place all full of bloud, they drewe the curtin and there found the poore body within the bed, ſleeping his long ſleepe. You may well thinke what ſorrowe his poore ſeruants made, that bare the body to his pallace, whither the Biſhop came, who told them how the Gentleman was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted by night in great haſte vnder pretence to go and ſee his brother: wherefore it was evidently found that it was he that had done the murther. And it was prooued that his poore ſiſter, had neuer heard thereof, who although ſhee was abaſhe at that had happened, yet ſhe loued her brother the more, that had deliuered her from ſo cruell a Prince, ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of her chaſtity, not hauing for the ſafegard thereof, feared to hazard his own life: and continued more and more her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and vertuous life, in ſuch ſort, that although ſhee was but poore, becauſe their houſe and goods was all confiſcate, yet ſhee and her ſiſter found as rich huſbands as any were in Italie, and euer ſince haue liued in great reputation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="novel">
               <head>The eleuenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The ſubtilty of an amorous gentleman, that vnder the fauour and countenance of a good friend, obtained of a Gentlewoman of Millan the fruits of his forepaſſed labours.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the dutchie of Millan at ſuch time as the great maſter of Chaumont was gouernor: there was a Gentleman named the Lord of Boniuet, who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for his vertues, was Admirall of France. Hee
<pb facs="tcp:21446:27"/> being at Millan welbeloued of the great Maſter and of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the vertues that were in him, vſed much to bankets where the Ladies and Gentlemen did reſort, of whome he was better eſteemed then euer any French man before him had beene, as well for his beuty, good grace, and pleaſant ſpeech, as for the report giuen of him, to be one of the valian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and ſtouteſt warriors that euer was in his time. Vpon a day being in a maſke in ſhroue weeke, he led one of the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt and faireſt Gentlewomen in all the Citty to dance with him, and when the hautboies pauſed, he failed not to ſolicite her with loue, which he knew better then others how to doe. But ſhe that was not behinde in anſwering him, would ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly caſt her fanne before her face and ſtay him, aſſuring him that ſhe loued not, nor euer would loue any but only her huſband, wiſhing him not to hope for any other at her hands. This anſwere made not the Gentleman to forbeare, but er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly purſued her, vntill lent: but for a reſolution he founde her firme and conſtant in determination, neither to loue him nor any other, which hee could not beleeue, conſidering the hard countenance of her huſband and her great beauty: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing ſhe ſo much diſſembled, he determined likewiſe to vſe deceipt. And from that time forwards left off his ſuite, and enquired ſo well of her life, that hee found ſhee loued a very wiſe and honeſt Gentleman of Italie: the ſaid Lord of Boniuet by little and little acquainted himſelfe with the ſaid Gentleman, in ſuch crafty and ſubtile manner that he neuer could perceiue, but he loued him ſo well, that after his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, he was the man that in the world he moſt loued. The Lord of Boniuet to find the ſecret of his heart, feined to ſhew him his, and that he loued a Gentlewoman whom hee neuer thought vpon, deſiring him to keepe his ſecret, and beſought him that their harts and mindes might be all one. The poore Gentleman to ſhewe him the like fauour tolde him at large of his loue he bare vnto the Gentlewoman, whereof Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uet ſought to be reuenged, and once a day they met in ſome place or other to ſhewe their good fortunes that day paſt,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:27"/> which the one told in good trueth, the other diſſembling. And the gentleman confeſſed that he had loued that gentlewoman for the ſpace of three yeeres together, without euer obtaining any other things at her hands, than only faire ſpeeches, with aſſurance to be beloued of her. The ſaid Boniuet counſelled him the beſt way hee coulde, to finde the meanes to bring his purpoſe to paſſe; whereby he found himſelfe ſo well eaſed, that in few daies after ſhe graunted him his deſire: and there reſted nothing but to finde the meanes to execute the ſame, which by the lorde Boniuets meanes was ſoone founde out.</p>
               <p>One day before ſupper the Gentleman ſaid vnto him. Sir I am more beholding to you than to al the men in the world, for that by your good counſel I hope this night to reape that I haue ſo manie yeares laboured to obtaine. I pray thee ſaid Boniuet ſhew me the manner of the enterpriſe, to ſee if there be deceit or hazard therein, that I may aide and ſerue thee as a friend. The Gentleman tolde him how ſhe meant to leaue the ſtreet doore open, vnder pretence of a certain diſeaſe that one of her brethren had, for whome at all times of the night they were forced to fetch ſome thing or other: and that hee might aſſuredly enter into the Court: but that hee was to take heede hee went not vp the great ſtaires, but rather, a ſmall paire of ſtaires on the right hand, and ſo enter into the firſt gallery, where hee ſhould finde that all the doores of the chambers of her father and brother in lawe did open, and that he ſhould chuſe the third doore neareſt vnto the ſaide ſtaires, and that if in thruſting it ſoftly from him he found it ſhut, hee ſhould not ſtay, beeing aſſured that her huſband was come, who neuertheleſſe was not to returne in two dayes, and that if he found it open, he ſhould go in ſoftly, and then ſhut it to him, knowing thereby not any body to be therein, but ſhe her ſelfe; and that aboue all, he ſhould not forget to make ſhooes of felt, fearing to make any noiſe, and that he ſhould likewiſe be ſure not to come before two hours after midnight, becauſe her brethren that loued play, neuer vſed to goe to bed before one of the clocke at night: the ſaide Boniuet anſwered him
<pb facs="tcp:21446:28"/> and ſaid: Go my friend, God be thy ſpeede, I beſeech him to keepe them from incumbrance, if my company may pleaſure thee, I will not ſpare any thing that is in my power. The Gentleman thanked him moſt heartily, and tolde him that in ſuch an enterpriſe he could not be too ſure, and went preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to take order for the ſame. The L. of Boniuet for his part ſlept not, and perceiuing it time to bee reuenged on his cruell Dame, withdrew himſelfe in good time vnto his lodging, and cauſed his beard to be cut of the ſame length and breadth that the Gentleman ware his beard, and cut his haires like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to the end that by touching, their difference might not be knowne: he forgate not his felt ſhoes, and the reſt of his apparell like vnto the Gentlewomans: and becauſe hee was much beloued of the father in lawe to that Gentlewoman, was not afraide to go thither in good time, thinking that if he were perceiued, he would go ſtrait vnto the old mans cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, with whom he had ſome buſines to do; and about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night entred into the gentlewomans houſe, where he found diuers of the houſe ſtirring, but yet hee paſſed and was not knowne, and ſo entred into the gallory; and touching the two firſt doores, he found them ſhut, but not the third, which he thruſt ſoftly from him, and being in the chamber, he ſhutte the doore to him, and perceiued all the chamber to be hanged with white linnen cloth, the floore and the roofe in like ſort, and a bed of linnen very fine, ſo well wrought with white worke as poſſible might be, and the Gentlewoman alone within the bedde in her ſmocke and a waſtecoate all ſet with pearles and ſtones, which he perceiued thorow the curtaines, not being ſeene of her, for there ſtood a great candle of white waxe vpon the table, that made her chamber ſeeme as light as day: but fearing to be knowen by her, he put it out: that done, he put off his clothes vnto his ſhirt, and layed himſelfe downe by her, ſhe thinking it had beene the Gentleman that had loued her ſo long, receiued him in as friendly manner as ſhe could: but he that knew it was done in the name of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man, would not ſpeake a word, but thought onely to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute
<pb facs="tcp:21446:28"/> his reuenge, which was to bereaue her, both of honour and chaſtitie, without giuing her thanks: but againſt his wil and determination, the Gentlewoman contented herſelfe ſo well with that reuenge, that ſhe thought ſhe had recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him well for his paines, vntill an houre after midnight, that it was time to bid her farewell, and then as ſoftly as he could, he aſked her if ſhe were as well content with him as he with her: ſhe thinking it had beene her friend, ſayde that ſhe was not onely content, but marueiled at his great loue, that had made him ſtay an whole houre from ſpeaking vnto her: with that he began to laugh, ſaying vnto her, Well Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, will you refuſe me another time, as til now you haue vſed to doe? She that knew him by his ſpeech and laughter, for ſhame was almoſt deſparate, and more then a thouſand times called him villaine, traitour, and couſiner, thinking to riſe out of the bed, to finde a knife to kill herſelfe, ſeeing ſhe had beene ſo accurſed, to loſe her honour, for a man ſhe loued not, and that to be reuenged on her, might make it knowen to all the world. But he held her in his armes, and by good and faire ſpeeches, aſſured her to loue her more then him ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> loued, and that he would be ſecret, in ſuch ſort that ſhe ſhould neuer heare it. Which the poore foole beleeued: and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his inuention, and the paines that he had taken for to win her, ſware ſhe would loue him better then the other, that could not keepe his ſecrets: and ſayd that ſhe then knew the contrary of the falſe report giuen of French men, for they were wiſer, more perceiuant, and diſcreet then the Italians: wherefore from thenceforward ſhe would deſiſt from her opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion touching his countreymen, to content her minde with him. But ſhe deſired him very earneſtly, that for a time he would not be in place, or banket where ſhe might come, but onely in a maſke, becauſe ſhe knew full well ſhe ſhould be ſo aſhamed, that her countenance would make it knowen to all the world. He promiſed her it ſhould be ſo, and prayed her that when her friend came about two of the clocke, that ſhee would bid him welcome, and that after by little and little ſhe
<pb facs="tcp:21446:29"/> might caſt him off. Whereof ſhe made ſo great difficultie, that but onely for the loue ſhe bare vnto him, ſhe would haue granted it. Neuertheleſſe in bidding him adue, he contented her ſo well, that ſhe would willingly haue had him ſtayd lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. After he was vp and made him ready, he went out of the chamber, and left the doore as he had found it: and becauſe it was almoſt two of the clocke after midnight, and that hee feared to meet the Gentleman in the way, he ſtayd at the top of the ſtaires, where preſently after he ſaw him paſſe by, and enter into the chamber. Which done hee went ſtraight vnto his lodging, to reſt him of his trauailes, in ſuch ſort, that at nine of the clocke in the morning they found him in his bed. When he was riſing, the Gentleman came in, that failed not to ſhew him his fortune, not ſo good as he hoped it ſhuld haue bene: for ſayd he, when I entred into the chamber, I found her vp, and ſet in her mantle, with a fit of an ague vpon her, her pulſes beating ſore, her face all in a colour and ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, her diſeaſe beginning to come vpon her, in ſuch maner, that ſhe deſired me preſently to depart, for that fearing ſome inconuenience, ſhe durſt not call her women, whereby ſhe was ſo ill at eaſe, that ſhe had more cauſe to thinke on death, then vpon loue, and rather to heare ſpeaking of God then of Cupid, being very ſory for the hazzard wherein I had put my ſelfe for her, ſeeing ſhe had not the meanes in this world to render mee the like, but ſhe hoped to doe it in the world to come. Whereat I was ſo abaſht, that my fier and ioy were turned into iſe and ſadnes, and ſo I preſently departed: and in the morning about breake of day I ſent to know how ſhee did, and newes were returned me of a certaine that ſhee was very ſicke: and ſaying ſo, he wept ſo bitterly, that it ſeemed he would yeeld his ſpirit with teares. Boniuet that had as much deſire to laugh as the other to weepe, comforted him the beſt he could: ſaying vnto him, that things of long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance haue alwaies a hard beginning, and that loue gaue him a delay to cauſe him to feele a enioying thereof to bee more pleaſant, and therewith they departed from each other.
<pb facs="tcp:21446:29"/> The Gentlewoman for certaine daies after kept her bedde, and recouering her health, gaue her firſt ſeruant his farewel, grounding it vpon the feare ſhe had of death, and remorce of conſcience, and contented her ſelfe with the lord of Boniuet, whereof the amity indured (according to the cuſtome) as the beauty of the flowers in the field.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="novel">
               <head>The twelfth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ Of a Gentlewoman in the Kings court, that perceiuing her ſelfe to be diſdained of her husband, that loued other women, ſhee reuenged her ſelfe by the like meanes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Court of King Francis, the firſt, there was a Gentleman whoſe name I know full well, but I wil not name it, he was but poore, as hauing but 500. frankes yearely rent, to liue on, but ſo much eſteemed of by the King, for the vertues wherewith he was indowed, that he maried ſo rich a wife, as that a great Lorde would haue contented himſelfe with her, and becauſe ſhee was very young, he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one of the greateſt Ladies in the court to keepe her in her houſe, which ſhee willingly did. This Gentleman was ſo honeſt and ſo full of good grace, that all the Ladies in the court made great account of him, and one among the reſt the King loued, yet not ſo faire nor ſo young as his owne, and for the great loue he bare vnto her he made ſo ſmall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his wife, that hardly once a yeare he lay with her, and which was more importable for her, was, that hee neuer ſpake vnto her, nor ſhewed any ſignes of loue: and although he enioyed her goods, yet he gaue her ſo ſmall a portion, that hardly was ſhe apparelled as her eſtate required, neither as ſhe deſired, whereby the Lady with whom ſhe was, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times reproued the Gentleman, ſaying vnto him: your wife is faire, rich and of a good houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and you eſteeme not of her,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:30"/> which her infancy and yong yeres hath borne vnto this time, but I feare that when ſhe ſhall perceiue her ſelfe to be faire and of good ſtature, that ſome one that loueth you not, ſeeing beauty (which to you is not eſteemed) will ſeeke to court her ſo, that in beſpight ſhe will do that, which being by you will vſed ſhe durſt not once conceale. The Gentleman that had ſet his heart in another place, mocked her, and for all that ceaſed not to follow his old courſe: but two or three yeares being paſt ouer, his wife began to bee one of the faireſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in all France, and ſo faire, that ſhe had the whole report in the court not to haue her match: and the more ſhe percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and felt her ſelfe worthy to be beloued, the more it grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued her to ſee her huſband, that made no account of her, in ſuch ſort, that ſhe tooke ſo great diſpleaſure thereat, that without the comforte of her miſtris ſhe was in a maner deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perace: and hauing ſought all meanes ſhe could to winne her huſbands loue, though with her ſelfe it was impoſſible, but that he ſhould loue her conſidering the great loue ſhe bare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, vnleſſe his minde were called otherwiſe, which ſhee ſo ſubtilly went about to know, that in time ſhe founde the truth, and that he euery night was ſo buſie elſewhere, that he forgot both his conſcience and his wife: and after ſhe was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the life he led, ſhe was ſo malancholy, that ſhe would weare nothing but blacke, nor haunt any places where mirth or good cheere was vſed. Which her miſtris perceining, did what ſhe could to withdraw her from this ſad conceit; but it was impoſſible and although her huſband were aduertiſed thereof, yet was he readier to mocke her, then to take any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therein. You know Gentlewoman that griefe ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ioie, and that griefe by ioy is ouercome. Wherefore it happened that a great Lorde neere kinſman vnto the miſtris of the Gentlewoman and that came often thither, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſtrange maner of the Gentlewomans huſband, had ſo great pitty on her, that he thought to try if he could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her: and ſpeaking with her found her ſo faire and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that he had more deſire to win her fauor, then to ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:21446:30"/> vnto her of her huſband: vnleſſe it were to ſhewe her what ſmall occaſion ſhe had to loue him.</p>
               <p>The Gentlewoman perceiuing her ſelfe forſaken of him that ought to loue hir, and on the other ſide loued, and ſought vnto of ſo great and faire a prince, counted her ſelfe happie to be ſo much in his fauour. And although ſhe alwayes deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to preſerue her honor, yet ſhe took great pleſure to ſpeake vnto him, and to ſee her ſelfe beloued; a thing whereof ſhee had great want. This loue continued for a time, vntill by chance the King perceiued it, who loued the Gentleman her huſband ſo well, that he would not ſuffer any man to procure his ſhame or diſpleaſure: wherefore hee deſired the prince to withdraw his minde, ſaying that if he did it not, he woulde be offended with him. The prince that loued the kings fauour and goodwill better than all the Ladies in the world, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him, that for his ſake he would leaue his enterpriſe, and that at night he would take his leaue of her: which he did as ſoone as he vnderſtood her to be in her lodging, and the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman himſelfe was lodged in a chamber ouer hers: and looking out of his chamber window, perceiued the prince to enter into his wifes chamber being vnder his. But the prince that ſaw him well, ſtaied not to enter, and bidding her adieu, whoſe loue as then did but beginne, tolde her the reaſon was becauſe the King had commaunded him ſo to do. After ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teares and ſighes that continued vntil an houre after mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, the gentlewoman for concluſion ſpake and ſaide: I thanke God (my Lord) that it hath pleaſed him to alter your opinion, ſeeing it is ſo ſmall and feeble that you can take and leaue it at mans commandement. For as for me I haue not aſked counſel either of miſtris, or of huſband, or of my ſelfe to loue you; for loue helping it ſelfe with your beautie and honeſtie, hath had ſuch power ouer me, that I haue not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen other God or King than it: but ſeeing your heart is not filled with ſo true loue, that feare as yet remaineth therein: you cannot be a perfect friend; and of an imperfect I wil not make afriend, for that I loue perfectly, as I had determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:21446:31"/> to loue you, but now (my lord) I am conſtrained to bid you farewell, whoſe feare doth not deſerue the freedome of my loue. With that the Lord departed weeping, and as he went away, he perceued her huſband ſtil ſtanding at the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, that had both ſeene him goe in and out: wherefore the next day he told him the occaſion why he went vnto his wife, and the commandement the King had giuen him, wherewith the Gentleman was wel pleaſed, and thanked the King: but ſeeing his wife daily to waxe fairer than ſhe was, and hee to the contrary became olde and leſſe beautifull, beganne to change courſe, taking that which he had cauſed his wife full often to vſe, for that he made more of her than vſually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e did, whereby he tooke more heed vnto her. But the more ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued herſelfe ſought vnto by him, the more ſhee eſtranged herſelfe from him, deſiring to giue him part of the ſorrowes and griefes ſhe had had, in beeing little beloued of him, and not ſo ſoone to lay hold on that pleaſure, which loue began to ſhew her, ſhe addreſſed her ſelfe vnto a young Gentleman ſo faire, ſo well ſpoken, and of ſo good a grace that he was belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of al the ladies in the court. And making her complaints vnto him, how ſhe had bin well vſed, mooued him to haue pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on her, in ſuch maner, that the Gentleman forgot not anie thing that might comfort her: and ſhe to recompence herſelfe for the loſſe of a prince that had forſaken her, ſet her loue ſo ſure vpon the gentleman, that ſhe forgat her ſorrow paſt, and thought of nothing elſe but howe to behaue her ſelfe therein, which ſhe could doe ſo well, that her miſtris neuer perceiued it, for ſhee neuer ſpake vnto him in her preſence. But when ſhe would ſpeake vnto him, ſhe went to viſite certaine ladies that lodged in the Court: among the which there was one whereof her huſband fained to be amorous; and vpon an eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after ſupper this gentlewoman ſtole out when it was darke without company, and went into the ladies chamber, wherein ſhe found him whome ſhe loued better than her ſelfe; and ſitting hard by him, leauing on a table, they ſpake toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, making ſemblance as if they had beene reading vppon a
<pb facs="tcp:21446:31"/> booke: but ſome one whome her huſband had appoynted to watch her, tolde him whither his wife was gone: hee being craftie, went preſently thither, and entring into the chamber, perceiued his wife reading in a booke, but making as though he ſawe her not, went among the ladies to ſpeake to them: The poore gentlewoman perceiuing her huſband had found her in his company, to whome in his preſence ſhe had neuer ſpoken, was in ſuch feare, that ſhe loſt all ſence; and hauing not the meanes to paſſe by a bench, ſhe ſlid along by a table, and came away, as if her huſband had folowed her with a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſword in his hand, and went into her miſtris chamber, who as then was come into her lodging; and when her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris was a bed, ſhe went into her owne chamber, where one of her maides tolde her, that her huſband aſked for her: ſhee boldly made anſwer, ſhe would not come at him, ſaying that he was ſo ſtrange and cruell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that ſhe feared he would do her ſome miſchiefe. But in the ende, leſt worſe ſhould happen, ſhee went vnto him: when ſhee came into his chamber, her huſband gaue her not a word before they were in bed, where ſhe that could not diſſemble, as he had done, began to weepe: And when he aſked wherefore ſhe wept, ſhe ſaide: becauſe ſhe feared he was angry with her, for that hee had found her by a gentleman reading in a booke. Whereunto he anſwered he had neuer forbidden her to ſpeake to any man, and that he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliked not of her ſpeaking to him, but for that ſhe ranne away, as if ſhe had done ſome thing worthy reproch, and that her running away made him verily ſuſpect ſhe loued the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: wherefore he forbade her, that from that time forward ſhe ſhould not ſpeake either priuately or publikely vnto anie man, aſſuring her, that the firſt time ſhe ſhuld do it, he would kill her without mercy, which ſhe promiſed to performe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her account at other times not to be ſo fooliſh. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in the things that we moſt deſire, the more wee are forbidden, ſo much the more we deſire them. This poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had ſoone forgotten her huſbands threatnings, for that the ſame night being returned to her chamber to lie with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:21446:32"/> gentlewomen that attended on hir: ſhe ſent to ſeeke the gentleman, deſiring him to come that night to ſee her. But hir huſband that was ſo plagued with iealouſie, that he could not ſleepe, roſe vp, and caſting a cloake vpon his ſhoulders, calling one of his ſeruants, went out of his chamber, bicauſe he had vnderſtoode that thy yong gentleman went thither by night, and went and knocked at his wiues chamber doore: ſhe that looked for nothing leſſe than her huſband, roſe vp, and putting a mantle about her, and perceuing that three or foure of her maids ſlept, went out of the chamber, and came to the doore where he knocked: and aſking, who is there? aunſwer was made in the gentlemans name that ſhe loued: but ſhe for more aſſurance opened a little hatch, ſaying: if you be hee you ſay you are, giue me your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; I ſhal know the better: and hauing touched hir huſbands hand, ſhe knew it well, and in all haſte ſhutting the hatch beganne to crie out: O ſir, it is your hand: her huſband anſwered her and ſaide; yea it is the hand that ſhall keepe promiſe with you, wherefore faile not to come when I ſend for you: and ſaying ſo he went vnto his lodging, and ſhe returned into her chamber rather dead than liuing, and ſpake aloude vnto her women ſaying: Vppe my friends you haue bin ouer ſleepy for me; for that I thinking to deceiue you, haue deceiued my ſelfe: and ſaying ſo ſhee ſounded and fell downe in the middle of the Chamber. The poore women at that crie roſe vp, much abaſhed to ſee their miſtris lie vpon the ground, and to heare the words ſhe ſpake ſo that they knew not what to do, but only to find meanes to recouer hir: and when ſhe could ſpeake, ſhe ſaid vnto them: this day (my friends) ſhall you ſee me the moſt miſerable cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature liuing on the earth; and therwith ſhewd them the cauſe, deſiring them to help hir, for that ſhe made ful account to loſe hir life.</p>
               <p>They thinking to comfort her, there came one of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemans ſeruants, that attended on him in his chamber, that tolde her his maiſter had ſent for her. She there at (imbracing two of her mayds beganne to weepe) deſiring them not to let
<pb facs="tcp:21446:32"/> her goe, ſeeing ſhe was aſſured to die. But the page aſſured her the contrary, and that he would venture his life, that the ſhould haue no hurt. She perceiuing that no reſiſtance would ſerue, caſt herſelfe into her ſeruants armes, ſaying vnto him, My friend, ſeeing it muſt be ſo, doe thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ary this vnhappy body vnto her death: and therewith, halfe dead with griefe, ſhe was borne by the page into her huſbandes lodging, at whoſe feete the poore Gentlewoman fell downe, and ſayde: Sir, I beſeech you to haue pity vpon me, and I ſweare vnto you, of my faith, I wil ſhew you the trueth of all. With that, like a deſparate man he ſayd: By God you ſhall tell me the trueth: and therewith ſent all his ſeruantes foorth. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had found his wife to be very deuout, he thought ſhe would not forſweare herſelfe, if that ſhee ſware vpon the croſſe: wherefore he called for a very faire Crucifire, that he had borrowed, and they two being alone together, made her ſweare by it, that ſhe would tell him trueth in whatſoeuer he ſhould aſke. But ſhee that already had paſt the firſt brunt of the feare of death, tooke comfort, determining before ſhee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not to hide any thing from him, and alſo not to tell him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing whereby the Gentleman whom ſhe loued, might ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteine any wrong: and hauing heard the queſtions hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, anſwered him, and ſayd: I will not iuſtifie my ſelfe, neither yet diſſemble the loue vnto you I beare vnto the Gentleman whome you ſuſpect, for that you neither can nor ought to beleeue it, conſidering the experience that this day you haue had, but I am very deſirous to ſhew you the occaſion thereof: wherefore, ſir you muſt vnderſtand that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any woman loued hir huſband ſo well as I loue you, for that ſince I married you vntill this time, there neuer entered any other loue into mine heart then onely yours: you knowe that I being a childe, my parents ſought to marry me vnto a man of greater renowme then yourſelfe, yet could they neuer make me agree unto it, after I once had ſpoken vnto you, for that againſt al their minds I remained conſtant, to haue you, not reſpecting your pouertie, my friendes inſtructions to the
<pb facs="tcp:21446:33"/> contrary: and you are not ignorant what interteinement I haue hitherto had of you, and how you haue loued and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med me, whereby I haue had ſo much ſorow and griefe, that without the helpe of my lady with whome you placed me, I was in maner deſparate: but in the end perceiuing my ſelfe to waxe of more yeeres, and of all men, except your ſelfe eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med faire. I began in ſuch ſort to feele the diſpleaſure of the wrong you did me, that the loue I bare vnto you, turned into hatred, and the deſire to pleaſe you, changed into reuenge: and in this diſpaire a prince reſorted to me, who to obey the king more then loue, left me at ſuch time as I began to feele the comfort of my torments by an honeſt loue: and leauing him, I found this Gentleman, that needed not to intreat me, for that his beauty, honeſty and vertues deſerued to be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ſought vnto of all women of good iudgement. At my requeſt, and not at his, he hath loued me, with ſo honeſt a minde, that neuer in his life did he require any thing of mee contrary to mine honour. And although the ſmall loue that I haue cauſe to beare vnto you, gaue me occaſion neither to ſhew faith nor loyalty vnto you, the loue which I onely beare to God and to mine honor, haue hitherto preſerued me from doing that, for the which I ſhould need any confeſſion, or feare of ſhame. I will not deny, but that as often as poſſible I could, I went to ſpeake with him in a gallery, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to go to prayer, for that I neuer put my truſt either in man or woman to be a meanes therein. I will likewiſe not deny, that being in ſo ſecret a place, and out of all ſuſpition, but that I kiſſed him with a better heart, then euer I kiſt you, but yet I neuer aſke mercy at Gods hands, if that betweene vs two there euer was other kinde of priuity, or euer he ſought more at my hands, or that euer my heart had other deſire, for that I was ſo well pleaſed to ſee him, that me thought there was no greater pleaſure in the world. And you ſir, that are the onely cauſe of my miſhap, would you be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denged on a deed, where you your ſelfe haue ſo long time gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me an example, yours being wholy without honour or
<pb facs="tcp:21446:33"/> conſcience? for you know and I am well aſſured, that ſhee whom you loue contenteth not her ſelfe with that which god and reaſon commandeth. And although the lawes of man do attribute ſo great diſhonor vnto women, that loue other men beſides their huſbands, yet it is ſo, that the lawe of God doeth not exempt the huſband that loueth other women then his wife: and if both our offences were put into a paire of ballance it would ſoone be tried which were heauieſt: you are a man in yeares, wiſe and of good experience, to knowe and vnderſtand how to auoid euill; I am young and wholy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out experience to know the force and power of loue. You haue a wife, that ſeeketh, loueth &amp; eſteemeth you, more then her owne life, and I haue a huſband that flieth from me, that hateth and deſpiſeth me, more then a poore ſeruant. You loue a woman already in yeares, and of no great beauty, in reſpect of me, and I loue a Gentleman younger, fairer, and amiabler then you. You loue the wife of one of the greateſt friends you haue in all the world, on the one ſide offending the Aunte, and on the other ſide the reuerence you beare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them both; and I loue a Gentleman that is not bound nor linked vnto any, but only to the loue he beareth me. Now ſir I pray you without partiality to iudge, which of vs two is moſt worthy of puniſhment or to be excuſed, I know not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man of experience, but would lay the fault on you, ſeeing that I am young and ignorant, deſpiſed and contenmed of you, &amp; loued of the faireſt &amp; honeſteſt Gentleman in France, whom I loue, being in deſpaire neuer to be beloued of you.</p>
               <p>The Gentleman hearing thoſe ſpeeches full of truth, and vttered with a countenance ſo faire, togither with ſo good a ſpirit, that thereby ſhe ſhewed not any feare to haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued puniſhment, found himſelfe ſo ſurpriſed with doubt, that he could make her no other anſwere, then only that the honor of a man and of a woman make no leſſe, nor yet all one, but that neuertheleſſe ſeeing ſhe ſware there was no ſin between her friend and her, he determin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d not to doe her any hurt, ſo that ſhee neuer vſed it againe: and that neither hee nor ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:21446:34"/> would euer call to minde their griefes and iniuries forepaſt, which ſhe promiſed to obſerue; and with that they went to bed, as good friends. In the morning an old Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was in great feare of her miſtris life, came vnto her when ſhe aroſe, aſking her and ſaid; well Madame howe doe you? ſhee anſwered her laughing, why ſweete heart, there is not a better huſband in the world then mine, for hee beleeued me vpon mine oath. In that maner fiue or ſix daies paſſed ouer, wherein the Gentleman ſo narrowly watched his wife, that both night and daie, ſhe had thoſe that looked to her: but he could not watch her ſo well but that ſhe ſpake vnto him ſhe loued in a very darke and ſuſpitious place. Yet ſhe did it ſo ſecretly that neither man nor woman could euer haue known it, had it not been for a report that a ſeruingman gaue foorth that he had ſound a Gentleman and a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman togither in a ſtall vnder the chamber of this Lady: whereat the Gentleman her huſband had ſo great ſuſpition, that he determined to kill the Gentleman, and to the ſame end aſſembled a great number of his kinſmen and friendes, that if they could finde him in any place to kill him: but his chiefe kinſeman was ſo great a friend vnto the Gentleman whom hee ſought for, that in ſteed of taking him, aduertiſed him what was done againſt him: who on the other ſide was ſo well beloued in the court, and ſo well accompanied that he feared not his enemies, ſo that he could not be found; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a Church, went in to the miſtris of his loue, that neuer had heard of any thing that had paſt, for that before her hee neuer ſpake vnto her. The Gentleman told her of the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and hatred her huſband bare vnto him, and that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his innocency he was determined to abſent himſelfe by ſome long voyadge, to auoide the ſuſpition already begon: the princes, miſtris to his friend, was much abaſht to heare thoſe ſpeeches, and ſware that the huſband did wrong to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſo honeſt a woman as his wife, in whom ſhe had neuer found other then vertue and honeſtie. Neuertheleſſe becauſe of the authority of her huſband, and to quench ſuſpition, the
<pb facs="tcp:21446:34"/> princes counſelled him to abſent himſelfe for a certaine time, aſſuring him that ſhe would not beleeue any of her huſbands folies or ſuſpitions. The Gentleman and the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man her wayting mayde were very well content to remaine in the good opinion and fauour of the princes, who counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Gentleman, that before his departure he ſhould ſpeake with her huſband, which he did, finding him in a gallery hard by the Kings chamber, where with a bold countenance (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him his due honour) he ſaide vnto him. Sir, I haue alwaies had a great deſire to doe you ſeruice, and for my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour I vnderſtand that the laſt night you ſought to kill mee, I beſeech you ſir remember that you haue more authority &amp; power then I haue, yet I am a Gentleman as well as you, it would grieue me much to looſe my life for nothing: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you likewiſe thinke that you haue an honeſt woman, and that if there be any man that will affirme the contrary, I will plainely tell him that he lyeth, and for my parte, I thinke I haue not done any thing wherby you ſhould haue cauſe to beare mee ill will; wherefore if it pleaſe you, I am your friend, if not I am the Kings, whereby I haue occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to content my ſelfe. The Gentleman to whom he ſpake ſayd, that truely he had had ſome ſuſpition of him, but that he accounted him ſo honeſt a man, that he would rather deſire his loue, then otherwiſe; and bidding him farewell with his hat in hand imbraced him as his great friend. You may wel thinke what they ſaid, which the night before had had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for to kill him, when they ſawe ſo great ſhewes of friendſhip and loue betweene them, whereof euery man did ſpeake: with that the Gentleman departed: but becauſe he was not ſo wel furniſhed of money as of beauty, his Lady gaue him a iewell worth 3000. crownes, which he layed to pawne for 1500. And not long after his departure the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Gentleman went vnto the chamber of the Princes, his wiues miſtris, deſiring her to giue his wife leaue for a time to lie at one of his ſiſters houſes: which the princes found ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry ſtrange, deſiring him to let her know the cauſe, who tolde
<pb facs="tcp:21446:35"/> her part, but not all. After the yong married Gentlewoman had taken her leaue of the princes, and of all the court with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out weeping or any ſigne of griefe, went vnto the place where her huſband had appointed, being in the conduct of a Gentleman that had expreſſe charge to looke carefully vnto her, and eſpecially that as ſhe rode in the way, ſhe ſhould not ſpeake vnto him for whom he ſuſpected her. She that knew her huſbands ſtraight commaundement, euery day during their iourney, gaue them ſome alarme, mocking both them and their negligent watch: and one day among the reſt, as they went out of their lodging, ſhe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a frier on horſebacke, and ſhe likewiſe on a gelding, enterteined him from noone till night: and being about a mile from their lodging, ſhe ſayd vnto him, Father, for the good counſels and comforts you haue giuen me this afternoon, there are two French crowns which I giue you, that are within a paper becauſe I know you dare not touch them, praying you that aſſoone as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me, you will gallop in all haſte ouer the fieldes. And when he was ſomewhat farre off from the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſhe ſpake aloud vnto her ſeruants, ſaying: Doe you thinke your ſelues good ſeruants, and careful of your charge, when he whom ye are expreſly commanded not to let ſpeake with me hath beene with me all this afternoone, and you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſought to hinder him: you deſerue that your maiſter, which truſteth ſo much in you, ſhould giue you blowes in ſtead of wages. When the Gentleman that had charge of her, heard thoſe ſpeeches, he was in ſuch a rage, that he could not ſpeake a word, but ſpurred his horſe, and calling two of the men with him, did ſo much that they ouertooke the frier: who ſeeing them come towards him, fied as faſt as he could, but becauſe they were better horſt then he they ouertook him, and he that knew not wherefore, cried them mercy, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off his hood with more humility to intreat them, they knew well it was not he they ſought, and that their miſtreſſe had mocked them, which ſhe did much more at their returne, ſaying vnto them: Such men as you, ought to haue the kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb facs="tcp:21446:35"/> of a woman, for when you haue letten her ſpeake you know not to whome, giuing credit to her words, you goe and do iniury to the ſeruants of God. And after all theſe mocks, ſhe atriued at the place where her huſband had appointed her to be, being by her two ſiſters in law, &amp; one of their huſbands kept in great ſubiection. Meane time her huſband vnderſtood that her iewellay at pawne for L500. crownes, for the which he was ſorry: but to ſaue his wiues credit, and to haue it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, he tolde her that ſhe ſhould fetch it, and he would pay the 1500. crownes. She that cared not for the iewell, ſeeing her friend had the money, wrote vnto him, how that her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band would conſtraine her to redeeme the iewell: and to the end he ſhould not thinke ſhe did it for want of good will, ſhee ſent him a diamond that her miſtreſſe had giuen her, which ſhee loued more then any iewell ſhee had. The Gentleman willingly ſent her the marchants obligation, and contented himſelfe to haue had 1500. crownes and a diamond, and to be aſſured of his friends good will, although that as long as her huſband liued he had no more meanes to ſpeake vnto her but by letters. And after her huſbands death, becauſe he thought her to be the ſame ſhe alwayes promiſed him, he vſed all the meanes he could to haue her in mariage. But he found that his long abſence had gotten her a friend whom ſhe loued bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: whereat he tooke ſuch griefe, that ſhunning all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>women, he ſought aduentures, where he obtained as much honour as any yong Gentleman could haue, and ſo ended his dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="novel">
               <head>The thirteenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ A Gentlewoman of Millan tried the boldneſſe and great courage of her louer, for the which after that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhe loued him perfectly.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the time of the great maiſter du Chaumont, there was a Gentlewoman eſteemed one of the honeſteſt women in her time liuing within the Citty of Millan, ſhe maryed an Italian Earle, whoſe widdow ſhe was, liuing in a houſe of her
<pb facs="tcp:21446:36"/> huſbands brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neuer caring or deſiring to heare any ſpeech of marying againe, behauing hir ſelfe ſo wiſely and ſo holily that there was not any French man or Italian within that Dutchie, which made not great account of her. Vpon a day as her brethren and her mother in lawe made a great feaſt for the great maiſter du Chamount, this Lady being a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow was conſtrayned to be there, which in other places ſhee vſed not: and when the French men ſawe her, they eſteemed much her beauty and good grace, ſpecially one whoſe name I will not diſcloſe: but it ſuffiſeth you to knowe that there was not any Frenchman in Italie worthier then he to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued; for that hee was adorned with all the beauties and good qualities a Gentleman may haue: and although he ſaw this Lady (being a widdow) wearing a blacke ſipres, ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the younger Ladies, and bearing company with the elder ſort, as one to whome man or woman coulde neuer procure feare, he began to entertaine her, taking away his vizard and leauing off to dance, that he might ſit by her, and all that night left not off to ſpeake vnto her, and the olde la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies togither, wherein he found more pleaſure then with all the braueſt and youngeſt Ladies in the court, in ſuch maner, that when he ſhould recite he thought hee had had the leiſure onely to ſit downe: and although he ſpake not to this Lady, but only of common matters, which might be ſpoken in ſuch company, yet ſhe perceiued wel he was deſirous to acquaint himſelfe with her: ſo that ſhe determined to abſtaine as much as poſſible ſhe might, in ſuch maner that he could neuer after finde her at any feaſt or banket: whereupon he enquired what her common exerciſes were, and found that ſhe often vſed to the Church and diuers religious houſes, where hee made ſo good watch, that ſhe could not go ſo ſecretly but hee was there before her, and that he ſtayed in the Church as long as he might haue meanes to ſee her, and that as long as he was ther he beheld her with ſo great affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ſhe could not be ignorant of the loue he bare her: which to avoid, ſhe determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for a time to faine her ſelfe ſick, and to heare maſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:21446:36"/> her houſe; whereat the Gentleman was ſo grieued as more he could not be, for that he had no other meanes to ſee her but onely as I ſaid before: ſhe thinking to haue broken off that cuſtome, went vnto the Churches as before ſhe vſed to doe, which loue preſently made knowen vnto the Gentleman who renewed his firſt deuotions, and fearing leaſt ſhe ſhould finde out ſome other means of hinderance, and that he might not haue the time to let her know his minde, one morning as ſhee thought her ſelfe well hidden within a little Chappell, where ſhe heard maſſe, he went and placed himſelf, at the end of the alter: and perceiuing that ſhe had but ſmal company, as the Prieſt held vp the Corpus Domini, he turned vnto her, and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h a vnfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpeech and great affection ſaid vnto her: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame, I take him whom the Prieſt holdeth in his hands for my damnation, if you onely be not the cauſe of my death, for although you take from me, all meanes of ſpeaking to you, yet can you not be ignorant of my deſire, ſeeing that truth ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently declareth it vnto you by my languiſhing eies, and dead countenance. The Lady counterfeiting not to know his meaning, anſwered him and ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; God ought not to be ſerued in this maner, but Poets doe commonly ſay, that Gods do laugh at the othes and lies of louers, wherfore women that loue their honours ought to be neither credulous nor pitifull. And ſaying ſo ſhe roſe and went vnto her lodging: if the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman was diſpleaſed at thoſe wordes they that haue tryed the like wil ſay yea: but he that wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted no courage, deſired ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that hard aunſwere, then to haue failed to declare his mind, which for the ſpace of three yeares he helde moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, and both by letters and other meanes ceaſed not dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſollicite her: but during three yeares ſpace, he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver obtaine other anſwere, but that ſhe fled from him, as the wolfe doth from the dogs, fearing to be taken, not for any hatred ſhe did heare vnto him, but for the danger of her ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, which hee perceiued ſo well that more earneſtly then before her followed his ſuit: and after many paines, refuſals, torments, and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſpaires, perceiuing the
<pb facs="tcp:21446:37"/> continuance of his loue, this Lady had pitty on him, &amp; gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him that he had ſo long and earneſtly deſired, and when they had agreed vpon the meanes, the French Gentleman failed not to haſſard him ſelfe to go vnto her houſe, although his life thereby might be in great danger, becauſe his kinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men lodged in the ſame houſe. He that had no leſſe ſubtilty then beauty, behaued himſelfe ſo wiſely, that he entered into her chamber at the time ſhe had appointed, where he founde her alone lying in a rich bed, and as he made haſte to put off his cloathes to go to bed vnto her, he heard a great noiſe of mens voyces ſpeaking ſoftly, and of ſwords that ſtrake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wals.</p>
               <p>The Lady with a face halfe dead ſaid vnto him, nowe at this time your life and my honour are in the greateſt danger that euer they were, for there I heare my brethren which ſeek for you to kill you: wherefore I pray you hide you vnder the bed, for when they finde you not, I ſhall haue an occaſion to be offended with them, for that without cauſe they haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me ſuch alarme. The Gentleman that as yet had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer been afraid ſayd vnto her, and what are your brethren to make an honeſt man afrayd? if all the race of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were heere in preſence, I am ſure they would not ſtay the fourth blowe that I ſhould giue, wherefore lie you ſtill, and let me keepe the dore: with that he wrapt his cloake about his arme, and hauing his ſword in hand, he went to open the dore to ſee his enemies weapons, whereof he heard the noyſe, and hauing opened it, he ſaw two maides that had two ſwordes in each hand, wherewith they gaue him that alarme, which ſaid vnto him, pardon vs ſir, for we haue commandment from our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteris to doe ſo: but you ſhall haue no more trouble by our meanes. The Gentleman perceiuing them to bee weomen, could not doe leſſe then wiſh them at the diuell, ſhutting the dore againſt them, and as ſoone as he could, went to bed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lady, whoſe feare had not in any thing diminiſhed his loue, and forgetting to aſke her the cauſes of her ſkirmiſhes, had no other thought but to ſatiſfie his deſire. But percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:21446:37"/> day to appeare, deſired her to tell him why he had done him that iniury, not onely in prolonging time, but alſo in that laſt enterpriſe, ſhe laughing anſwered him, ſaying: my deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination was neuer to loue which ſure my widdowe-hood I had alwaies obſerued, but your honeſty from the time you ſpake vnto me, at the banket made me, change opinion, and that I began as then to loue you as much as you loued me, it is true chst lone which alwaies guided me, would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit that loue ſhould cauſe me doe the thing wherby mine ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour ſhould be ought impaired but as the hinde wounded to death, thinketh in changing places, to change the euill which ſhe heareth in her body, ſo I went from Church to Church thinking to flie that which I bare within my heart, whereof I haue made ſo perfect proofe, that it hath made mine honor to conſent vnto my loue, but to the end I might be well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to place my loue and my heart in a perfect honeſt man, I thought to make this proofe which my maides haue now ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, aſſuring you, that for feare of life or other reſpect, I had found you fearefull, ſo that you had hidden your ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my bed, I was determined to haue riſen, and haue gone into another chamber, without euer ſeeing you more: but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue found you faire, of good grace, and full of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and hardines, more then was certifyed vnto me, and that feare could not ouercome your heart, nor in any ſort leſſen the loue you beare vnto me, I am dotermined to content my ſelfe with you, vntill I die, being aſſured that I cannot put my life and honour into a better hand, then in his, whoſe like for vertues I neuer found. And ſo as if the mindes of men were not mutable they ſware and promiſed that which was not in their powers, that is a perpetuall amity, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpring nor yet dwell in mans heart, and they knowe it well, that haue tried and known how long ſuch opinions doe continue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="novel">
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:38"/>
               <head>The foureteenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ A poore ſimple country man, whoſe wife loued the Curate of the Church ſuffereth himſelfe eaſily to be deceaued.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the County of Maime, in a villadge called Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celles there was a rich huſbandman, that in his age had maried a faire young wench, that had no children by him: but for the loſſe ſhe had by him, till the recompenced her ſelfe with other men, and when gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and other good companions failed ſhe turned to her laſt reliefe, which was the Church, and made him compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of her ſinne, that could obſolue her, which was the Curat, that oftentimes came to viſit his ſheepe. The huſband be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old and craſie, ſuſpected nothing, but becauſe he was rude and churliſh, his wife plaied her part as ſecretly as ſhee could, fearing that if her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhould perceiue it, he would kill her. Vpon a day as he was abroad, his wife thinking hee would come ſo ſoone againe, ſent for the Curate to confeſſe her, and as they made good there togither, her huſband came in vpon the ſodaine, whereby the Curate had not leiſure to go vnto his houſe, but deuiſed meanes to hide himſelfe, and by the womans counſell went into a barne, and couered the ſtaires head where he went vp with a fanne of corne, the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band being in the houſe; ſhe leaſt he ſhould ſuſpect her, made him ſo good cheere to dinner, that ſhe ſpared no drink, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he tooke ſo much, that togither with the wearines he had by labouring in the fieldes, he fell a ſleepe, ſitting in a chaire before the fier. The Curate being weary to be ſo long in the barne, hearing no noyſe in the chamber, went vnto the ſtairs, &amp; thruſting out his necke as farre as he could to looke down, perceiued the good man to be a ſleepe, and looking earneſtly vpon him, leand ſo hardly vpon the fanne, that both fanne and he fell vnto the ground, hard by the old man that ſlept, where
<pb facs="tcp:21446:38"/> with he waked: the Curate that aroſe vp ſooner then the man could open his eies, ſaid vnto him there is your fanne, and I thanke you, wherewith he went his way, and the poore man being abaſht aſked what it was: ſhe anſwered him, it is your fanne that the Curate borrowed, and nowe hath brought it home, he grumbling ſaid, doe men vſe to bring home things they borrowe in ſuch rude maner, I thought the houſe would haue fallen downe, by which meanes the Curate ſaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the poore mans coſt, that found fault with nothing but that he brought his fanne ſo rudely home.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="novel">
               <head>The fifteenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ The ſtrange fragilitie of man, that to couer his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour falleth from euil to worſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the time of king Lewes the twelfth, one of the houſe of Ambois nephew to the legate of France named George, being legate in Auigneon, had in the country of Languedoc a Lady, whoſe name I wil not rehearſe for her kinreds ſake, that had better than foure thouſand crownes yearely reuenue: ſhe being very yong was a widow, and had but one child, being a ſonne; and for griefe ſhe had for the loſſe of her huſband, as alſo for the loue of her ſonne, determined not to marry againe. And to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde all occaſions would not vſe the company of any other than religious perſons, thinking that ſinne cauſeth temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whereby the yong widow gaue her ſelfe only to diuine ſeruice, wholy forſaking worldly company, in ſuch manner that ſhe made conſcience to goe to any wedding, or to heare the Organs play within the church. When her ſonne was ſeuen yeares olde, ſhee choſe a man of zealous life to be his ſchoolemaiſter, by whoſe good meanes he might be brought vp in godlineſſe. When hir ſonne entred into his fifteenth yeare, Nature, which of it ſelfe is a ſecret Schoolemaiſter,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:39"/> finding him too delicately nouriſhed, and full of idleneſſe, taught him an other leſſon, than his maiſter vſed to do, for that he beganne to beholde and reſpect thinges that ſeemed faire; and among the reſt a gentlewoman that lodged in his mothers chamber, wherof no man euer doubted, for that they no more reſpected him, than a yong infant; no other thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpoken of in the whole houſe but godlineſſe. This yong gentleman began ſecretly to ſeek vnto the maid that told it to her miſtris, who loued and eſteemed her ſonne ſo much, that ſhe ſuſpected the maide to tell it her, onely to make her hate him: but ſhe was ſo importunate with her miſtris, that ſhee ſaid vnto her, I wil know if it be true, and aſſure your ſelfe I wil correct him if I finde it to be ſo: but if you tell mee an vntruth, I wil make you feele the price thereof. And to finde the trueth ſhe willed her to appoint her ſonne to come about midnight to lie with her in a bed neere vnto the doore of the chamber where the maid lay. The maid obeyed her miſtris: and when night came the Gentlewoman laide her ſelfe in hir maides bed, determining if it were true, to correct her ſonne ſo well, that neuer after he ſhould deſire to lie with maide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. And in that thought and diſpleaſure her ſonne came to bed vnto her. She, although ſhe ſaw him lie downe, would not yet beleeue he would commit any diſhoneſt art, but ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſpeake with him, vntil ſhe perceiued ſome ſignes of bad deſire: but not being perſuaded with ſo ſmall a ſigne, that he would proceed further, was ſo long pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient, and ſo fraile of nature, that ſhe conuerted her choller into a moſt abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pleaſure, forgetting the name of mother: and euen as water that by force is holden in, when it iſſueth foorth, mek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth more noyſe than that which runneth his ordinary courſe, ſo this poore lady turned her glory into the reſtraint ſhe gaue vnto her body. And when ſhe proceeded to decline from the firſt degree of honeſtie, ſhe found her ſelfe ſodainly caried and borne vnto the laſt; and the ſaide night became with child by him, whom ſhe ſought to keepe from getting others with childe. The ſame was no ſooner committed, but the remorce
<pb facs="tcp:21446:39"/> of conſcience, brought her into into ſo great torment, that the repentance neuer left her during her whole life, which at the firſt was ſo ſharp, that ſhe roſe out of the bed from her ſonne, that knew no other but it had bin the maid, and went into a cloſet, where calling her good determination vnto mind, and the wicked execution thereof, ſhe paſſed al the night in weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and lamenting all alone: but in ſtead of acknowledging of the impoſſiblitie of our fleſh, that without Gods help, can not but ſinne, deſiring by her ſelfe, and by her teares to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie hir fault paſt, and by hir wiſedome to auoyde the euill to come, ſhe laide the excuſe of her ſinne vpon the occaſion, and vpon the weakenes of fleſh and blood, whereunto there is no remedy but only by the grace of God: ſhe thought to do that, whereby in time to come ſhe might not fal into the like incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd as though there were but one kinde of ſinne to damne men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he deuiſed all the meanes ſhe could to auoyde the ſame. Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the roote of pride which externall ſinne ſhould heale, increaſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> her heart, in ſuch maner, that by auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one miſchiefe ſhe fel into diuers others: for the next mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning as ſonne as it was day, ſhe ſent for her ſonnes Schoole maiſter and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aid vnto him; Now my ſon beginneth to wax great, it is time to ſend him abroade. I haue a kinſman that dwelleth beyond the mountains with Mouſis the great mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter du Chaumont that will be very glad to haue him in his company, wherefore I pray you bring him thither: and to thend I be not grieued with his departure, let him not come to take his leaue of me. And ſaying ſo, ſhe gaue him money to beare his charges for the voyage: and the ſame morning cauſed the yong gentleman to depart, that was very glad at nothing elſe than after the inioying the pleaſure of his loue, to goe vnto the wars. The lady continued long time in great melancholy and diſtreſſe; and had it not bin for the feare of God, ſhe had often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed the end of the vnfort<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nat fruit ſhe bare within her bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. In the end ſhe fained to be ſicke, that vnder that vnder th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> might couer her imperfection: and being re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dy to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, remembring that there was no
<pb facs="tcp:21446:40"/> man in the world in whome ſhe ſo much truſted, as a baſtard brother of hers, whom ſhe intertained &amp; did him much good; ſhe ſent for him, and ſhewing him her hard fortune (but made him not acquainted that it was by her ſonne) deſired him to help her, and to ſaue her honour, which he did: and not long before ſhe ſhould lie downe, he gaue her counſell to chaunge the aire, and to go to his houſe, where ſhe might ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer her health than in her owne. She went thither but with ſmall traine, and there ſhe found a midwife ready for her, that by night not knowing her, brought her to bed of a fayre daughter: the gentleman deliuered it vnto a nurſe, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to be nurſed for his owne. The Lady hauing ſtayed there a moneth, went home vnto her owne houſe, where after that ſhe liued more ſtrictly than euer ſhe did, both in faſting and diſcipline. But when her ſonne became great, perceiuing no warre to be in Italie, he ſent to deſire his mother that hee might come ſee her: ſhee fearing to fall into the euill from whence ſhe had eſcaped, would not permit him, till in thend he was ſo importunate with her, that ſhe had no reaſon to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him. Neuertheleſſe ſhe ſent him word, that he ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come vnto her, if he were not married to a wife that he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued wel; and that he ſhould not reſpect her riches, ſo ſhe were honeſt, and it ſhould ſuffice. In the meane time baſtard brother perceiuing the daughter whereof he had the charge, to waxe great, &amp; very faire, thought to place her in ſome houſe farre off, where ſhee ſhould not be knowne; and by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers counſell, gaue her vnto the Queene of Nauarre. This daughter named Katharine grew to the age of twelue or thirteene yeres, and became ſo faire &amp; honeſt, that the Q. of Nauarre bare her good affection, and deſired much to mary her richly. But by reaſon ſhe was poore, ſhe found her ſelfe to haue ſuters great ſtore, but none that would bee her huſband. Vpon a day it happened that the Gentleman that was her vnknowne father, returning from the other ſide of the Alpes, went vnto the Queene of Nauarres houſe, where he had no ſooner eſpied the mayd, but he became amarous of
<pb facs="tcp:21446:40"/> her, and bicauſe he had licence of his mother to mary one that liked him, he tooke no care but onely to haue a wife that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his fantaſie, and knowing her to be ſuch, aſked her in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of the Queen, that moſt willingly conſented as know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Gentleman to be rich, and with his riches both faire and honeſt. The mariage being finiſhed the Gentleman wrot vnto his mother that from thencefoorth ſhe neede not refuſe him her houſe, for ſeeing he brought with him as faire a wife as any could be found, the Gentlewoman that enquired with what houſe he had matched himſelfe, found hee had maried their owne daughter, wherwith ſhe was in ſuch deſpaire, that he preſently thought to die, perceiuing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more ſhe ſought to hinder her griefe, the more ſhe was the means to increaſe the ſame. Whereupon not knowing what to doe, ſhe went vnto the Legate being at Auignion, to whom ſhe confeſſed the greatnes of her ſinne, aſking his counſell what ſhe ſhould doe therein. The Legat to ſatiſfie her deſire, ſent for certaine deuines, to whom he vttered the matter not naming the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; found by their counſel, that the Gentlewoman ought not to make it knowne vnto her children, for that for their parts conſidering their ignorance, they had not ſinned, but that ſhe during her life ought to do penance without making any ſhew thereof. Which done, the poore woman returned home, where not long after ariued her ſonne and her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in lawe that loued ſo wel, that neuer huſband nor wife lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in better ſort, for ſhe was both his daughter, ſiſter, and wife, &amp; he too her father, brother and huſband; in which great amity they continued long: and the poore Gentlewoman in her extreame penance, that neuer ſawe them merry, but ſhee withdrew her ſelfe to weepe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="novel">
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:41"/>
               <head>The ſixteenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ Of a merry conceited Bricke-layer, that had a curſt queane to his wife, and of that which happened.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the towne of Bleare nere Aragon, there is a village called S. Mortis the faire, where there dwelt a handſome propper fellow, as any in Paris, where he was borne; and for his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour he durſt haue trauailed into any Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans buttery, where all the barrels had beene full, without either dagger or ſword about him. For his reſolution, if he had once gotten vnder a maydes chamber window, he would neuer haue ſtarted, till they had emptied a chamber pot on his head. For his courage he durſt haue gone into any baudy houſe, and would haue come out againe as honeſt a man as when he went firſt in. For his credit, he might haue runne on the ſcore for ſixe pots with any Alewife that kept houſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in fiue miles where he dwelt. For his qualities euery maner of way, he had the preheminence amongſt all the youths that were in thoſe quarters; for at Maytide, who was the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leader for the fetching home of a Maypole, but he? at Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummer he was choſen the Summer lord: at euery bridall, who muſt dance with the bride, but luſty Roger? Thus for a pleaſant life, the Conſtable of Paris liued not more merrily then he. And for his reputation, he was almoſt as much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerenced as our Churchwardens. But as the ſtouteſt ſtand of ale at laſt is ſet on tilt, and the fatteſt gooſe comes ſooneſt to the ſpitte; ſo his former fortunes were drawen to the lateſt date, and his prime of pleaſures concluded with miſhap. But oh loue, oh cruell loue, that was the firſt fruit to his felicities. But who can reſiſt loue, if it be once crept into the bottome of a mans belly? oh what a rumbling it makes in his gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, and how it bethrobs him about the heart. And ſee now the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele of his miſhappe: he fortuned to be at a ſheepſhearing,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:41"/> where he met with a pretie wench, named Siſly, in a fine red peticoate, with damaſke vpper bodies, a white apron before her: and vpon her head a broad felt hat, with a braue branch of roſemary ſticking in her boſome, appointed amongſt the reſt with a paire of ſheares to helpe ſheare ſheep, and he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing brought foorth a luſty yoong ramme, would haue laide him in her lappe; but ſhe refuſing to take him, ſaid vnto him: Now good friend Roger, if you loue me, bring me none but polde ſheepe; for of all things in the world, I cannot abide theſe horned beaſts. When he heard theſe milde words, that gently ſpoken, and how kindly ſhe pronounced this ſentence (Good friend Roger, if you loue me) oh heauens (thought he) what a ſweet charme is this? then noting her modeſtie, that ſhe could not abide the ſight of an horned beaſt, he began to thinke with himſelfe, how happy might that man be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted that could light of ſuch a wife. And hauing but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle giuen ſcope to his owne affections, loue that had his tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der boxe ready to ſtrike fire, by this time had ſet his fancy of ſuch a flame, that not longer able to endure the heat without a cup of ſacke, he ſayd vnto her: Siſter, your maner of phraſe hath wonderfully troubled me: for in your firſt ſpeeches you call me your good friend Roger, and then you came in with a doubtfull demand, in theſe words (if you do loue me) as though I could be your good friend, and yet did not loue you: but Siſley, ſith you haue popt me ſuch a doubtfull que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, if you and I were alone by our ſelues, I would pop you ſuch an anſwere, that you ſhould well finde that I loued you, and that hereafter you might leaue out your, If, and ſay Roger Aſſe you loue me.</p>
               <p>With theſe words, pretily caſting her head at one ſide, ſhe gaue him ſuch a leering looke, that might aſwell haue danted him with diſpaire, as gaue him comfort and hope of grace, for the one of her eyes was bleared, and ſeemed as though ſhee wept, the other was a prety pinkeny, looking euer as though ſhee ſmiled, ſo that in her very countenance at one inſtance, you might eaſely beholde pleaſure, and paine, pitie, and ri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gour,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:42"/> curteſie and crueltie, loue and diſdaine; and then with a ſweet voice, like one that were aſking an almes, ſhe ſayd: Roger, if you loue me as you ſay, your loue ſhall not be loſt: but men are ſo crafty now adayes before they are married, that they will make a mayde beleeue they loue her, till they haue got vp her belly, and then they wil not ſtick to deny their owne children, and that makes women when they be once maried, to play their huſbands ſuch a caſt, that they ſhall not know their owne children, but if your loue be no ſuch loue, Roger, you ſhall not finde me vnkinde: when he heard the wiſedome of the wench, it made his pulces ſo to beate, that he had thought his codpiſſe point would haue broken a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: but for an anſwere he ſaid.</p>
               <p>Siſly, your ſober ſpeeches ſo wiſely deliuered, togither with your ſweete countenance ſo liuely placed, hath ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed with your good friend Roger, that for the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of my loue receaue here this token, as a pledge of my good will, and taking then a twopenny piece which hee had in his purſe, he bowed it and gaue it vnto her, the which when ſhe had receiued, ſhe ſaid.</p>
               <p>Well Roger, now I doe account you as mine owne, and at night when my mother is gone to bedde, if you will come home, we will there talke further of this matter: and for your welcome I will beſtowe of you a meſſe of creame.</p>
               <p>Siſly, (ſayd he) looke you keepe your promiſe, for I wilbe there, and becauſe you will be at ſo much coſt with a meſſe of creame, I will bring with me a penny worth of ſpice cakes: and although they had thus referred their further ſpeeches til their next meeting, yet during the time that they remained there in place, many amarous glances, &amp; louing countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, there paſſed ſtill too and fro between them: but at night the appointed time being come, thither he went, and Siſly, was at the window watching for his comming, who hauing once eſpied him, ſhe opened the dore, where ſhe receiued him with ſuch a ſweete kiſſe, as if her breath had beene lately per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed for the purpoſe, whoſe dainty ſmell was as ſavery, as
<pb facs="tcp:21446:42"/> if it had beene a red herring that had beene newly roſted, her louely lippes pleaſant and ſoft, like a locke of wool, that was but then come out of the ſeame baſket: but ſhould I tell you of al the other loue tricks that paſſed betwixt him and her that night, I might either oppreſſe your ſtomacks to thinke of it, or otherwiſe perhaps make you aſhamed to heare it. But let this ſuffice, before they departed their mariage day was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and Siſly, in time made her mother acquainted with the matter, who nothing miſliking of her daughters choyſe, gaue her her bleſſing, with many other good helps to furniſh foorth her bridall day: the which when time had drawen to be ſolemnized, &amp; that the luſty youths of the pariſh were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered togither to go with vs to Church, and the young dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels were flocked on a heape to waite on the bride, attending her comming foorth, the good olde woman her mother, who had beene euer chary of the louely chickin her daughter, and euen at the very inſtant when we were ready to go to church, ſhe was ſchooling of her with this exhortation.</p>
               <p>Siſly (ſaid ſhe) the day is now come which you haue ſo much longed after, it is twenty yeares ago ſince you firſt wiſhed for a huſband, &amp; byrlady daughter, you were then ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteene or eighteene yeares of age, ſo that at this preſent you want not aboue two or three of forty: now if wit went by yeares, you are olde enough to be wiſe: but I being your mother, beſides my many yeares, which might aduance my ſkill: ſo I haue buried foure ſeuerall huſbands (the heauens he praiſed for it) which hath ſo much the more confirmed my experience in the diſpoſitions of men, and can the better iudge of their naturall inclinations: and by all that I haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by my own proofe and practiſe, I haue found it ſtill by triall, that the fantaſies of men, are euer beſt fitted with the follies of women: but leauing generalities, and to come to ſo much as concerneth but thy ſelfe, thou art now to be mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a huſband, who in reſpect of his age thou mightſt be his mother: and couldeſt thou now but conſider, what a comfort it is for an old woman, to be imbraced by a young man, O
<pb facs="tcp:21446:43"/> daughter daughter, thy mothers mouth beginnes to water, but with the very imagination to thinke of the pleaſure, and therefore happy maieſt thou deeme thy ſelfe, that art ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to inioy it.</p>
               <p>But here is now agreat piece of diſcretion to be vſed, for as age conceiueth ſuch contentment with the ſociety of fleſh and pleaſant youth, ſo youth will quickly fall a loathing of olde and croked age, if the parties be not wiſe to enforce that by art, that they are otherwiſe deuaied by nature: which is, to ſhew a youthfull diſpoſed minde how farre ſoeuer they be ſpent in yeares, for it is a tyred iade that cannot cry wee hee, and a ſorie mare that cannot wag her taile: thou art nowe to conſider the inequality of the yeares betweene thy ſelfe and thy huſband: and therefore a little to whet him on to make him to like the better of thee, it ſhall not be a miſſe for thee to ſhewe ſome youthfull conceipt, eſpecially being thy bridall day, it is tollerable for thee a little to play the wanton. I tel thee daughter, men are well pleaſed to ſee their wiues youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully giuen, as there is nothing doth more delight them, then to ſee them wantonly diſpoſed: and this is the means to win your huſbands liking, &amp; to draw him to that appetite, which your many yeares might quench, remember therefore what I haue tolde you, and faile not for your aduantage, to ſhewe ſome youthfull tricke.</p>
               <p>Siſly, making a manerly curteſie, ſayd: yes forſooth mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I will remember all that you haue tolde me: by this time all things being prepared, to Church they went, where the Prieſt hauing once done his office, they returned againe, and were accompanied with her neighbours and friends that went home to dinner with them, for whom there was provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded furmentie, and minced pies, beſides other good meates both roſt and ſad, the which being all ready, Siſlie was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the vpper end, between two of the moſt ſubſtantial ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt men according to the cuſtome of the pariſh and himſelfe likewiſe (as the maner was) did wait that day at the table with a napkin hanging on his ſhoulder.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:43"/>
               <p> But o what a comfort it was vnto him, to ſee how daine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily Siſly fed of euery diſh that came to the table, and howe luſtily ſhe layd about her for her victuals, and (though hee) if it be true as ſome men ſay, that a good feeding horſe will go through with his labour, then I warrdnt you if I giue Siſlie her meate, I neede not feare to ride her where I liſt: but dinner being almoſt at an end, and the cakebread &amp; cheeſe readie to be ſet on the table, the good old woman her mother who had likewiſe beene very buſie that daie in taking paines to fill the pots, &amp; to carie away empty diſhes, began to cheere vp the companie, bidding them welcome, and telling them ſhe was ſorie there was no better cheere for them.</p>
               <p>Siſlie, preſently vpon the ſight of her mother, bethought her ſelfe what ſhe had to doe, and calling now to minde what leſſon ſhe had giuen her, and how ſhe had willed her that day to ſhew ſome youthfull tricke, thereby to purchaſe the favor of her huſband, and picking out at that very inſtant a ſitte op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to perfourme it, ſhe called to her mother, in this youthful maner, Mamma, vp and cack, the old woman hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her daughter, ſaid: why how now Siſlie, fie for ſhame, will you ſpeake bugs words? could you not pretily haue ſaid I pray you mother haue me vp to picke a roaſe, nay now I ſee you plaie the wanton too much, then ſpeaking to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie that ſate by, ſhe ſaid: I pray you bear with my daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters childiſhnes, for I know it is the furmentie that doth ſo much annoy her, for euen from her infancie, if ſhee had taken any ſpoone meat, ſhe was ſtil troubled in the bottome of her backe ſide with a great ventoſity.</p>
               <p>The neighbours ſeeing the cleanelineſſe of the wench, did euer after that call her by the name of manerly Siſly. Let this ſuffice: within a very few months after he was maried, Siſly began to grow ielous: for if ſhe had bin once thirſty, and that he wanted money to ſend to the alehouſe, ſhe would tell him that hee ſpent away his thrift amongeſt ſome other yong queanes. Here began our firſt falling out: and to ſet forward the matter, there dwelt at the very next houſe by him
<pb facs="tcp:21446:44"/> a Taylor that had a wife, who was ſure once a day to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the breadth of her huſbands ſhoulders with his owne metyarde.</p>
               <p>Siſly and this Taylors wife grew to be acquainted: and amongſt other concluſions it was agreed between them, that to preuent diſeaſes, &amp; to preſerue them in health, they would euery morning next their hearts, take a phyſicall diet, which was, a full quarte of the quinteſſence drawne from an Ale tub, warmed by the fire, with a grated nutmeg, halfe a yeard of blacke pudding roſted, a quantitie of ſalt, with a meaſure of fine wheat flower, firſt made into paſte, and after baked in a loafe of bread: theſe ingrediences after they had incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together, they would afterwardes lightly faſt till noone: and they found ſuch a commoditie in vſing the medicine, that if the Taylor and he had not euery morning giuen them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to pay for the ſimples, it had not beene good for them to come that day after in their ſights; for the Taylors wife ſhe could handle a metyeard or a cudgell paſſing nimbly. But Siſly had gotten the practiſe of all manner of weapons; and beſides that, ſhe had the vſe of her nailes, which ſhe employed many times about my face: ſhe could likewiſe handle a paire of bellowes about my pate, a paire of tonges a thwart my ſhinnes, a firebrand ſometimes ſhould flie at my head, a ladle full of ſcalding liquor otherwhiles in my boſome, a three foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſtoole, a pot, a candleſticke, or any other thing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer came next her hand, all was one to her; and ſhe had lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſuch a dexteritie in the deliuerie, that they ſhoulde haue come whirling about my eares. But in thend, hee deuiſing with himſelfe a remedy for theſe miſchiefes, he found means to be made the Conſtable, hoping that his office would haue bin a protection to him for a yeare, and that ſhee durſt not haue ſtricken her Maieſties Officer. But within a day or two, it was his fortune to finde out a pot of ſtrong ale, which ſhe had ſet vp in a corner for her owne drinking; and he (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thirſtie) gaue it ſuch a ſoope, that hee left very little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde; the which afterward when ſhe came to ſeeke for, and
<pb facs="tcp:21446:44"/> found her ſtore ſo pittifully impaired, againſt his comming home at night, ſhe prouided her of a waſter: and hee was no ſooner entred the doores, but foorth ſhe comes with her cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell in her hand, and with ſuch a terrible countenaunce, that were able to affright any man that ſhould behold it.</p>
               <p>Roger (ſaid ſhe) I had thought you would neuer haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me occaſion to be iealous of you; but now I ſee you loue a cup of ſtrong ale better than you loue me: and do you not thinke then that I haue great reaſon to be diſpleaſed with your vnkindeneſſe towards mee, and to beate out that lacke of loue that cauſeth you ſo lightly to regard me? Siſly (ſaid he) take heed what you do, for you know that I am her Maieſties Officer, and here I charge you in the Queenes name that you hold your handes. What maſter Conſtable (ſaid ſhe) haue you gotten an inchantment for me? or do you thinke that your charme ſhall ſerue to excuſe you? No ſure, no, for now you haue deſerued double puniſhment: firſt, you being an officer, if you offer wrong, your puniſhment muſt be ſo much the more grieuous: and is it not meere iniuſtice to take that which was not prouided for you? Next, you haue deſerued to be wel puniſhed, for the little reuerence you haue vſed in the execution of your office, commaunding mee in the Queenes name to holde my handes with your cappe on your head, nor vſing any other duetie or reuerence. But maiſter Conſtable, I will teach you how to vſe an office: and with that ſhe let flie at his head, ſhoulders, and armes, and woulde ſtill crie, Remember heere after how you doe your office, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your duety to the Queene; remember when you do commaund in her Maieſties name, that you put off your cap, and do it with reuerence; and ſuch a number of other remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances ſhe gaue him, as (I thinke) there was neuer poore Conſtable before nor ſince, ſo inſtructed in an office as hee was. To tell of many other like remembrances which at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther times ſhe beſtowed on him, would be but tedious: but the concluſion is, he is now rid of her, ſhe being dead, heele keepe himſelfe a widower (for her ſake) as long as he liueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="novel">
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:45"/>
               <head>The ſeuenteenth Nouell.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>¶ Mahomet one of the Turkiſh Emperours, executes curſed cruelty vpon a Greeke maiden, whom he tooke priſoner at the winning of Conſtantinople.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F you do euer make any proofe or triall, to know of what trampe the arrowes of loue be, &amp; what fruit they bring to them that do vſe &amp; practiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I am aſſured you ſhalbe touched with ſome pitie when you vnderſtand the beaſtly crueltie of an Infidell louer towards his Ladie. He of whom I will declare the hiſtory is <hi>Mahomet,</hi> not the falſe prophet, but the great grandfather of <hi>Soliman Otiman</hi> Emperour of the Turkes, which reigned at that time: he it is that to the ſhame and eternall infamie of all Chriſtian Princes of his time, did winne Conſtantinople, and tooke away the Eaſt empire from <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian emperour. <hi>Mahomet</hi> then hauing obtained ſo great a victorie at Conſtantinople, among the ſpoiles of that rich ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, there was a fond Greeke maiden, of ſuch rare and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent beauty, as ſhe allured the eyes of euery wight to wonder and beholde her, as a thing miraculous, whoſe name was <hi>Hyerenae,</hi> of the age of ſixteene or ſeuenteene yeeres, whom a Captaine to gratifie his Lord did preſent: a iewell (as hee thought) moſt acceptable vnto him, aboue all things of the world. The emperour <hi>Mahomet,</hi> yong and wanton beyond meaſure, after that he had caſt his eye vpon the yong maiden, &amp; had grauen her beauty in his heart, gaue a ſtraight charge that ſhe ſhould be kept for him, hoping after the tumult of the warre was ended, to beſtow conuenient time vpon her. The retreict ſounded, and the affairs of the empire reduced to ſure eſtate, remembring himſelfe of the beauty of <hi>Hyerence,</hi> which had made a breach and entrie into his heart, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that ſhe ſhould be brought foorth vnto him, and hauing viewed her at his pleaſure, he felt himſelfe ſurpriſed with the new flame, that he conceiued no other delight, but to play and dallie with her, in ſuch ſort, as his ſpirits being in loues full poſſeſſion, loue dealt with him ſo cruelly, as he could take no
<pb facs="tcp:21446:45"/> reſt day nor night, who yeelded himſelfe ſuch a pray to his darling <hi>Hyerence,</hi> that he felt none other contentation in his minde, but that which he receiued of her. And this amorous paſſion endured the ſpace of three yeeres, taking ſuch vigour and increaſe by little and little, that he beganne to forget that which apperteined to the ornament and honor of his empire, leauing the whole adminiſtration of publike cauſes vnto his <hi>Baſchats,</hi> he himſelfe being ſo negligent, as he repoſed in them all matters concerning the ſtate of the empire. During this diſorder, the vulgar people began ſecretly to grudge, as well for the confuſion and diſorder of the empire, as for the ill gouernment of the ſame (and ſpecially becauſe the <hi>Baſchats</hi> corrupted with auarice, imployed themſelues to the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar profit, and to inrich themſelues with the ſpoile of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:) the <hi>Ianiſaries</hi> on the other ſide a warlike people, and brought vp in continuall exerciſe of armes, began with open voice to detract and ſlander their lord, commonly complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how he conſumed his life like an effeminate perſon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out inferring or doing any profit to the empire. To be ſhort, the matter came to ſuch deſolation, as it might rather haue bene called a ſedition, then a murmure: &amp; yet there was none ſo hardy, as durſt attempt to declare the ſame to the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, knowing him to be of nature terrible, cruel &amp; rigorous, that with a word would put him to death that went about to withdrawe him from his deſire: ſo that hee was ſo drunke with the beautie of the Greeke, that the leaſt matter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they might giue occaſion to withdraw him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent life, was enough to draw him into rage and fury. This poore emperour was ſo bewitched, as not onely he conſumed dayes &amp; nights with her, but he burned with continual ielou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, whoſe beauty was ſo liuely painted in the inward parts of his minde and heart, that he remained thus ouerwhelmed in beaſtly pleaſure. Euery man in particular, &amp; all in generall conſpired againſt him with one determinate minde, to yeeld no more obedience vnto him in time to come, and purpoſed to chuſe ſome emperour that were more warlike and martiall,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:46"/> through whoſe ſuccour and counſell they might not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the things gotten, but amplifie the bounds &amp; limits of their empire. <hi>Muſtapha</hi> which was brought vp with the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, a gentle perſonage, franke of talke, and ſo neere to his maieſty, that he might go into his chamber although y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Greeke was preſent: when he perceiued conuenient time, ſuch as he deſired to haue, repaired to the emperour vpon a day, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wel of his deuices, walked alone with him into his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: to whom after he had made great reuerence, according to their cuſtome, he ſayd: My ſouereigne lord &amp; maſter, if I might ſpeake freely, without ſeruile feare, which ſtayeth me, or if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> terror of your diſpleaſure might not abaſh me, I would willingly declare vnto your maieſty that which concerneth not onely your ſecurity &amp; ſauegard, but (which is more) the ſafety of your whole empire. Whome <hi>Mahomet</hi> anſwered with mery countenance, in theſe words: Caſt away ſuch cold feare as ſtayth thee, &amp; ſpeake hardly thy mind, ſhew me what it is that toucheth me. I doubt, &amp; it ſhall pleaſe your maieſtie, leſt I ſhall ſeeme ouer preſumptuous, and raſh, if Idiſcouer the ſecrets of my heart; but ouer ancient education, the duty of my conſcience, with the experience that you haue alwayes had of my fidelity, haue ſo much forced me, as being no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger able to rule my ſelfe, I am conſtrained (by what vertuous prouocation I know not) to manifeſt things vnto you, that both time &amp; neceſſity will make you thinke them good &amp; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary: although (it may ſo be) that now your eies be ſo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp in the vaile of your diſordinate affection, that you can not digeſt or take the ſame in good part. The life (my lord) which you haue led ſince the taking of Conſtantinople, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſiue pleaſures wherein you haue bene plunged theſe three yeres; is occaſion, that not only your ſouldiers, and the reſt of your popular people, but the moſt faithfull lords of your em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, do murmure, conſpire, &amp; coniure againſt you: and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me (my lord) if I ſpeake ſo vnreuerently in things tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching your preſeruation, for there is no man, but doeth verie much marueile of this great &amp; new alteration that appeareth
<pb facs="tcp:21446:46"/> in you, which doeth ſo abaſe you, &amp; maketh you to degenerate from your ancient generoſitie &amp; valiance: your ſelfe hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ouer your ſelfe to be a ſpoile &amp; pray to a ſimple woman, that you wholly depend vpon her flatteries &amp; allurements; reaſon or counſell can take no place in your paſſionate &amp; affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted heart: but I humbly beſeech your maieſty to enter a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle into your ſelf, and make a ſuruey of your life that you haue led theſe three yeres paſt. The glory of your anceſtors acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and come by ſo much ſhedding of ſo much bloud, kept by ſo great prudence, conſerued by ſo happy counſell, haue they no repreſentation or ſhew before your face? the remembrance of their memorable victories, doeth it not touch the depth of your conſcience? the magnanimitie &amp; valiance, wherby they be immortalized, and their fame regiſtred thorow the whole world, is it extinguiſhed in you? their trophees &amp; monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts gotten, and aduanced to all the corners of the earth, be they throwen downe and defaced, from the ſiege of your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance? But where is now the ardent deſire which boiled in you from your infancie, to make Italie tributarie vnto you, and to cauſe your ſelfe to be crowned at Rome, emperour aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of the Orient as of the Occident? this is not the way to amplifie and enlarge your empire, but rather to reſtraine and diminiſh the ſame: this is not the way to preſerue it, but to ſpoile it, and to make it leſſe. If <hi>Ottomon</hi> the firſt Turke or ſtocke of your gentle familie &amp; kinred, had thus giuen him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be corrupted in idleneſſe, you had not now inherited the noble kingdome of Greece, nor gouerned the countries of <hi>Galatia</hi> and <hi>Bithinia,</hi> and many other prouinces, which inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone the great ſea. Semblably his ſonne <hi>Orcan</hi> (a liuely i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of his father, and a folower of his valiant facts, had not triumphed ouer <hi>Licaonia, Phrigia, Caria,</hi> nor dilated the bounds of his empire, to <hi>Helleſponte.</hi> What ſhall I ſpeake of <hi>Amurates</hi> the ſucceſſor of <hi>Orcan,</hi> who was the firſt that inuaded <hi>Europa,</hi> conquered <hi>Thrafia, Siria, Raſia,</hi> and <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia.</hi> and <hi>Baiazet</hi> likewiſe, did not he cut off the head of the great <hi>Tamberlaine,</hi> which called himſelfe the ſcourge of
<pb facs="tcp:21446:47"/> God, and brought into the field foure hundreth thouſand Sithians a horſebacke, and ſixe hundreth thouſand footmen? ſhall I paſſe ouer with ſilence the curteous exploites of your grandfather, Mahomet, who conquered Maſedonia, and made the countries to feele the edge of his ſword, euen to the ſea Tonicom, letting paſſe manie wonderfull expeditions and iornies, by him made againſt the Lidians, and Scicilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: but nowe I cannot reuiue the memorie of your father Amurate, but to my great ſorrow &amp; griefe, who by the ſpace of fortie years, made the ſea and earth to tremble and quake and with the furie of his ſtrong hand, vſed ſuch cruell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengment ouer the greeks, that the memorie of the wounds doe remaine at this daie, euen to the mountaines of Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mao, and Pindus, he ſubiugated the Phecians: made tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie Athens, Boetia, Aetolia, Caramania, and all the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous nations, from Morea, to the ſtraites of Cornitte, what need I here to bring in the cruel battaile that he fought with the Emperour Sigiſmounde, and Phillippe Duke of Burgundia, wherein he ouerthrewe the whole force of the chriſtians, tooke the Emperour priſoner, and the Duke of Burgundia alſo, whom he ſent to Andrionopolis; or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member other fierce armies which he ſent into Hungaria, whereof your Maieſtie is a faithfull witnes, your ſelfe being ſtill there in your owne perſon.</p>
               <p>Iudge then my Lord what diligent and intollerable tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel he vſed in his manifold glorious enterpriſes, and famous victories, doe you thinke that if he had beene idle in his pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, amongſt the Ladies you had inherited your Empire or had now beene Lord of ſo manie provinces; which he is not ſufficient to rule, that cannot prouide to confirm, and eſtabliſh the ſame: there be many of your ſubiects and vaſſals at this day, that doe obey and honour your Maieſty, more for feare, than good loue they beare you, that would rebel againſt you, if fortune would turne her back. The chriſtians of long time (as you know) haue ſworne your ruine &amp; deſtruction: moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſay that their high biſhop the Pope of Rome, hath
<pb facs="tcp:21446:47"/> conuocated al his prelates to vnite, &amp; reconciled the princes and monarchs of chriſtendome togither to ouerrun you, &amp; to take the ſcepter out of your hands, &amp; to diſpoile you of your empire, but what know we whether theyle ioine their forces with the power of the Perſian Sophi, your capital enemy, or with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouldan of Aegypt, your ancient aduerſary, which if it come to paſſe (as god forbid) your Empire wil be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: gather your wits then togither, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth my Lord &amp; cal againe reaſon, which ſo many yeares you haue baniſhed away from you: awake out of the deepe ſleepe, that hath ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp your eies, imitate &amp; follow the ſteps of your anceſtors which euer loued better one day of honor then a hundreth li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yeares of ſhame and reproch, attend to the gouernment of your empire, leaue off this effeminate life, receiue againe the ſmell of your generoſitie and vertue, and if you cannot at one time cut off &amp; remoue all that amarous heate, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermineth ſo your heart, moderat the ſame by little and litle, and giue ſome hope to your people, which thinke you to be vtterly loſt, and deſperate of recouery, or if ſo be the greeke doe ſo much delight you, who ſhall let you to cary her with you in al your iornies and expeditions? why, cannot you both inioy her beautie togither, and vſe the practiſe of armes? me thinke that your pleaſure ſhalbe greater after you haue won ſome victory, and ſubdued ſome countrie, to enioy her in your armes, then to remaine in a houſe with eternall infamy, and continuall grudging of your ſubiects: but proue I praie you, to ſeperate your ſelfe certaine daies from her, and you ſhall certainly iudge, how far more paſſing, the pleaſure be ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, then thoſe that be daily vſed: yet one thing more, &amp; it pleaſe your Maieſtie, there reſteth to be ſaid, which is, that al the victories of your progenitors, or the conqueſts, which your ſelfe hath made, be to ſmal purpoſe if you doe not keepe them, &amp; encreaſe them, the keeping of a thing gotten, being of no leſſe glory and praiſe, than the conqueſt: be now then a conquerour of your ſelfe, humblie beſeeching your Maieſtie, that if I haue ſpoken any thing, diſagreeable to your minde,
<pb facs="tcp:21446:48"/> according to your wonted clemencie to pardon the ſame, and to impute the fault to my bounden duetie, and the care that I haue of your honor and ſafetie. Mahomet, after he had heard the long diſcourſe of this ſlaue, ſtood as ſtill as a blocke, and fixing his eies vpon the ground, with ſodaine change of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, declared by outward ſignes, the cogitations and vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etnes of his mind in ſuch wiſe, as the poore ſlaue Muſtapha, ſeeing in him thoſe alteratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, was in doubt of his life; whoſe words ſo pricked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperors heart, that he knew not what to doe, or whereupon to be reſolued: and feeling his concience troubled with a furious battel, knowing euidentlie that Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtapha had ſpoken the truth, and that he vttered the ſame like a truſtie ſeruant to his maiſter: but on the other ſide the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the greek was ſtill before his eies, and the mind he had to abandon her, gaue him ſuch alarme, that he ſeemed at that inſtant, as though his heart had beene torne out of his bellie, and thus moued with diuers tempeſts, and diſquieted with ſundrie thoughts, hauing his eies inflamed with great rage and furie, he ſaid vnto him: although thou haſt ſpoken vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerentlie enough, yet our education togither, and the fidelitie that I haue prooued in thee in time paſt ſhall be thy pardone for this time. To the purpoſe; before the ſunne doth compas the Zodiacke, I will let it be knowen to thee and other, what puiſſance and power, gouernes mee, whether I am able to bridle mine affection or not; take order in the mean time, that all my noble men, the Baſchats, and the principall of my men of war, be aſſembled togither to morrowe in the midſt of the great hall of my pallace. This determination finiſhed, the Emperour went into the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke with whom hee reioiced all that day and night, and made more of her then euer he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and the more to flatter her, he dined with her, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that after dinner, ſhe ſhould adorne herſelfe with her beſt iewels, and deck her with the coſtlieſt apparell ſhee had: whereunto the poore wench obeied, not knowing that it was her funeral garments: on the other ſide Muſtapha vncertain of the Emperors minde at the hower appointed, cauſed al the
<pb facs="tcp:21446:48"/> nobilitie to be aſſembled in the hall, euerie of them maruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling what moued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour ſo to doe, ſince he had ſo long time ſhut vp himſelfe, without ſhewing his perſon abroade: being thus aſſembled, and euery man talking diuerſly of this matter, according as the affection ſerued: behold the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour entred the hall, leading the Greeke by the hand, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adorned otherwiſe than ſhe was wont to be, was accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied and garniſhed with beautie, ſo rare and excellent that ſhe reſembled rather an heauenlie Goddeſſe, then a humaine creature: the Turke being come into the hall, after that the Lordes had made their reuerence, according to the woonted maner, he holding ſtil the faire greeke and the left hand, and ſtoode ſtill in the midſt of the ſame, looking furiouſlie round about him, he ſaid vnto them. So farre as I vnderſtand, all you doe mutine and grudge, becauſe I (being vanquiſhed with loue) cannot be deuided, nor yet content my ſelfe day nor night from the preſence of this greeke: but I doe knowe none of you all ſo continent, and chaſte in loue, that if he had in poſſeſſion, a thing ſo rare and pretious, ſo amiable, indow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with beautie ſo excellent, but before he could forget her, and gitie her ouer, hee would three times be well aduiſed. What ſaie you to the matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euerie of you ſhall haue free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertie, francklie to tell me your minde: but they rapt with an incredible admiration, to ſee ſo faire a thing, ſaide that he had with great reaſon paſſed his time with her. Whereunto the barbarous cruell prince aunſwered: well, now then I will make you to vnderſtand, that there is no earthly thing that can binde vp, or captiuate my ſences ſo much, but that from henceforth I will follow the glorie, of mine anceſtors, and imitate the valiance of the Ottomans, which is ſo fixed in my breſt, as nothing but death is able to blot it out of my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance. Thoſe wordes finiſhed, incontinently with one of his handes, hee catched the Greeke by the haire of the head, and with his other hand, he drewe foorth his falchion from his ſide, and folding his hands about her golden locks, at one blowe, he ſtrake of her head, to the great terrour of
<pb facs="tcp:21446:49"/> them all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when he had ſo done, he ſaid vnto them: Now ye knowe, whether your Emperour is able to repreſſe, and bridle hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions, or not. Within a while after, meaning to diſcharge the reſt of his choler, he adreſſed a camp of foure ſcore or an hundreth thouſand men: with whome piercing Boſſiue, he beſieged Belgrade, where fortune was ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie vnto him that he was put to flight, and loſt there a notable battaile againſt the chriſtians, vnder the conduct of John Huniades, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named le Blancke.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:21446:49"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
